<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Exoplanet Atmospheres | Nicolas Iro</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/tag/exoplanet-atmospheres.html</link>
      <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/tag/exoplanet-atmospheres/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Exoplanet Atmospheres</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 01 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>http://localhost:1313/media/logo_hu_a8d074ae3d848875.png</url>
      <title>Exoplanet Atmospheres</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/tag/exoplanet-atmospheres.html</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>The CUISINES Framework for Conducting Exoplanet Model Intercomparison Projects, Version 1.0</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publications/2024-psj-5-175-s.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publications/2024-psj-5-175-s.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As JWST begins to return observations, it is more important than ever that
exoplanet climate models can consistently and correctly predict the observability
of exoplanets, retrieval of their data, and interpretation of planetary environments
from that data. Model intercomparisons play a crucial role in this context, especially
now when few data are available to validate model predictions. The CUISINES Working
Group of NASA&amp;rsquo;s Nexus for Exoplanet Systems Science supports a systematic approach
to evaluating the performance of exoplanet models and provides here a framework
for conducting community-organized exoplanet model intercomparison projects (exoMIPs).
The CUISINES framework adapts Earth climate community practices specifically for
the needs of the exoplanet researchers, encompassing a range of model types, planetary
targets, and parameter space studies. It is intended to help researchers to work
collectively, equitably, and openly toward common goals. The CUISINES framework
rests on five principles: (1) define in advance what research question(s) the
exoMIP is intended to address, (2) create an experimental design that maximizes
community participation and advertise it widely, (3) plan a project timeline that
allows all exoMIP members to participate fully, (4) generate data products from
model output for direct comparison to observations, and (5) create a data management
plan that is workable in the present and scalable for the future. Within the first
years of its existence, CUISINES is already providing logistical support to 10
exoMIPs and will continue to host annual workshops for further community feedback
and presentation of new exoMIP ideas.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Detection of Carbon Monoxide&#39;s 4.6 Micron Fundamental Band Structure in WASP-39b&#39;s Atmosphere with JWST NIRSpec G395H</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publications/2023-ap-j-949-l-15-g.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publications/2023-ap-j-949-l-15-g.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Carbon monoxide (CO) is predicted to be the dominant carbon-bearing molecule
in giant planet atmospheres and, along with water, is important for discerning the
oxygen and therefore carbon-to- oxygen ratio of these planets. The fundamental absorption
mode of CO has a broad, double-branched structure composed of many individual absorption
lines from 4.3 to 5.1 ensuremathμm, which can now be spectroscopically measured
with JWST. Here we present a technique for detecting the rotational sub-band structure
of CO at medium resolution with the NIRSpec G395H instrument. We use a single transit
observation of the hot Jupiter WASP-39b from the JWST Transiting Exoplanet Community
Early Release Science (JTEC ERS) program at the native resolution of the instrument
(R åisebox-0.5ex~ 2700) to resolve the CO absorption structure. We robustly detect
absorption by CO, with an increase in transit depth of 264 ensuremath± 68 ppm, in
agreement with the predicted CO contribution from the best-fit model at low resolution.
This detection confirms our theoretical expectations that CO is the dominant carbon-bearing
molecule in WASP-39b&amp;rsquo;s atmosphere and further supports the conclusions of low C/O
and supersolar metallicities presented in the JTEC ERS papers for WASP-39b.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
