<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Astrophysics - High Energy Astrophysical Phenomena | Nicolas Iro</title><link>https://ironick.github.io/tag/astrophysics-high-energy-astrophysical-phenomena.html</link><atom:link href="https://ironick.github.io/tag/astrophysics-high-energy-astrophysical-phenomena/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><description>Astrophysics - High Energy Astrophysical Phenomena</description><generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 01 Feb 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><image><url>https://ironick.github.io/media/logo_hu3811882414585691295.png</url><title>Astrophysics - High Energy Astrophysical Phenomena</title><link>https://ironick.github.io/tag/astrophysics-high-energy-astrophysical-phenomena.html</link></image><item><title>Impact of Cosmic Rays on Atmospheric Ion Chemistry and Spectral Transmission Features of TRAPPIST-1e</title><link>https://ironick.github.io/publications/2024-ap-j-961-164-h.html</link><pubDate>Thu, 01 Feb 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ironick.github.io/publications/2024-ap-j-961-164-h.html</guid><description>&lt;p>Ongoing observing projects like the James Webb Space Telescope and future
missions offer the chance to characterize Earth-like exoplanetary atmospheres. Thereby,
M dwarfs are preferred targets for transit observations, for example, due to their
favorable planet–star contrast ratio. However, the radiation and particle environment
of these cool stars could be far more extreme than what we know from the Sun. Thus,
knowing the stellar radiation and particle environment and its possible influence
on detectable biosignatures—in particular, signs of life like ozone and methane—is
crucial to understanding upcoming transit spectra. In this study, with the help
of our unique model suite INCREASE, we investigate the impact of a strong stellar
energetic particle event on the atmospheric ionization, neutral and ion chemistry,
and atmospheric biosignatures of TRAPPIST-1e. Therefore, transit spectra for six
scenarios are simulated. We find that a Carrington-like event drastically increases
atmospheric ionization and induces substantial changes in ion chemistry and spectral
transmission features: all scenarios show high event- induced amounts of nitrogen
dioxide (i.e., at 6.2 ensuremathμm), a reduction of the atmospheric transit depth
in all water bands (i.e., at 5.5–7.0 ensuremathμm), a decrease of the methane bands
(i.e., at 3.0–3.5 ensuremathμm), and depletion of ozone (i.e., at ensuremath∼9.6
ensuremathμm). Therefore, it is essential to include high-energy particle effects
to correctly assign biosignature signals from, e.g., ozone and methane. We further
show that the nitric acid feature at 11.0–12.0 ensuremathμm, discussed as a proxy
for stellar particle contamination, is absent in wet-dead atmospheres.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>