<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Planets and Satellites: Atmospheres | Nicolas Iro</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/tag/planets-and-satellites-atmospheres.html</link>
      <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/tag/planets-and-satellites-atmospheres/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Planets and Satellites: Atmospheres</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 01 Jul 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>http://localhost:1313/media/logo_hu_a8d074ae3d848875.png</url>
      <title>Planets and Satellites: Atmospheres</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/tag/planets-and-satellites-atmospheres.html</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dark skies of the slightly eccentric WASP-18 b from its optical-to-infrared dayside emission</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publications/2025-aa-699-a-150-d.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jul 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publications/2025-aa-699-a-150-d.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Context. Ultra-hot Jupiters (UHJs) are gas giant exoplanets that are strongly
irradiated by their star, setting intense molecular dissociation that leads to atmospheric
chemistry dominated by ions and atoms. These conditions inhibit day-to-night heat
redistribution, which results in high temperature contrasts. Phase-curve observations
over several passbands offer insights on the thermal structure and properties of
these extreme atmospheres. Aims. We aim to perform a joint analysis of multiple
observations of WASP-18 b from the visible to the mid- infrared, using data from
CHEOPS, TESS, and Spitzer. Our purpose is to characterise the planetary atmosphere
with a consistent view over the large wavelength range covered, including JWST data.
Methods. We implemented a model for the planetary signal including transits, occultations,
phase signal, ellipsoidal variations, Doppler boosting, and light travel time. We
performed a joint fit of more than 250 eclipse events and derived the atmospheric
properties using general circulation models (GCMs) and retrieval analyses. Results.
We obtained new ephemerides with unprecedented precisions of 1 second and 1.4 millisecond
on the time of inferior conjunction and orbital period, respectively. We computed
a planetary radius of R $_ p $ = 1.1926 ensuremath± 0.0077 R $_ J $ with a precision
of 0.65% (or 550 km). Based on a timing inconsistency with JWST, we discuss and
confirm the orbital eccentricity (e = 0.00852 ensuremath± 0.00091). We also constrain
the argument of periastron to ensuremathømega = 261.9$_‑1.4$ $^+1.3$ deg. We show
that the large dayside emission implies the presence of magnetic drag and super-solar
metallicity. We find a steep thermally inverted gradient in the planetary atmosphere,
which is common for UHJs. We detected the presence of strong CO emission lines at
4.5 ensuremathμm from an excess of dayside brightness in the Spitzer/IRAC/Channel
2 passband. Using these models to constrain the reflected contribution in the CHEOPS
passband, we derived an extremely low geometric albedo of A$_g$ $^CHEOPS$ = 0.027
ensuremath± 0.011. Conclusions. The orbital eccentricity remains a potential challenge
for planetary dynamics that might require further study given the short-period massive
planet and despite the young age of the system. The characterisation of the atmosphere
of WASP-18 b reveals the necessity to account for magnetic friction and super-solar
metallicity to explain the full picture of the dayside emission. We find the planetary
dayside to be extremely unreflective; however, when juxtaposing TESS and CHEOPS
data, we get hints of increased scattering efficiency in the visible, likely due
to Rayleigh scattering.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The effect of a biosphere on the habitable timespan of stagnant-lid planets and implications for the atmospheric spectrum</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publications/2025-aa-693-a-205-h.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publications/2025-aa-693-a-205-h.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Temperature-dependent biological productivity controls silicate weathering
and thereby extends the potential habitable timespan of Earth. Models and theoretical
considerations indicate that the runaway greenhouse on Earth-like exoplanets is
generally accompanied by a dramatic increase in atmospheric H$_2$O and CO$_2$, which
might be observed with the upcoming generation of space telescopes. If an active
biosphere extends the habitable timespan of exoplanets similarly to Earth, observing
the atmospheric spectra of exoplanets near the inner edge of the habitable zone
could then give insights into whether the planet is inhabited. Here, we explore
this idea for Earth-like stagnant-lid planets. We find that while for a reduced
mantle, a surface biosphere extends the habitable timespan of the planet by about
1 Gyr, for more oxidising conditions, the biologically enhanced rate of weathering
becomes increasingly compensated for by an increased supply rate of CO$_2$ to the
atmosphere. Observationally, the resulting difference in atmospheric CO$_2$ near
the inner edge of the habitable zone is clearly distinguishable between biotic planets
with active weathering and abiotic planets that have experienced a runaway greenhouse.
For an efficient hydrological cycle, the increased bioproductivity also leads to
a CH$_4$ biosignature observable with JWST. As the planet becomes uninhabitable,
the H$_2$O infrared absorption bands dominate, but the 4.3-textmum CO$_2$ band remains
a clear window into the CO$_2$ abundances. In summary, while the effect of life
on the carbonate-silicate cycle leaves a record in the atmospheric spectrum of Earth-like
stagnant-lid planets, future work is needed especially to determine the tectonic
state and composition of exoplanets and to push forward the development of the next
generation of space telescopes.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Understanding the atmospheric properties and chemical composition of the ultra-hot Jupiter HAT-P-7b. III. Changing ionisation and the emergence of an ionosphere</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publications/2021-aa-648-a-80-h.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publications/2021-aa-648-a-80-h.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Context. Ultra-hot Jupiters are the hottest exoplanets that have been discovered
so far. They present a unique possibility to explore hot and cold chemistry on
one object. The tidally locked ultra- hot Jupiter HAT-P-7b has a day-to-night
temperature difference of ≃2500 K, confining cloud formation to the nightside
and efficient ionisation to the dayside. Both have distinct observational signatures.
Aims: We analyse plasma and magnetic processes in the atmosphere of the ultra-hot
Jupiter HAT-P-7b to investigate the formation of an ionosphere and the possibility
of magnetically coupling the atmospheric gas as the base for an extended exosphere.
We show which ions and atoms may be used as spectral tracers, and if and where
conditions for lightning may occur within the clouds of HAT-P-7b.  Methods: We
used 3D modelling results as input for a kinetic cloud formation code and evaluated
characteristic plasma and magnetic coupling parameters. A local thermodynamical
equilibrium radiative transfer was solved for the ionised gas phase. This study&lt;br&gt;
is confined to thermal ionisation only.  Results: The ionisation throughout HAT-P-7b&amp;rsquo;s
atmosphere varies drastically between day- and nightside. The dayside has high
levels of thermal ionisation and long-range electromagnetic interactions dominate
over kinetic electron-neutral interactions, suggesting a day-night difference
in magnetic coupling. K$^+$, Na$^+$, Li$^+$, Ca$^+$, and Al$^+$ are more abundant
than their atomic counterparts on the dayside. The minimum magnetic flux density
for electrons for magnetic coupling is B &amp;lt; 0.5 G for all regions of HAT-P-7b&amp;rsquo;s
atmosphere.  Conclusions: HAT-P-7b&amp;rsquo;s dayside has an asymmetric ionosphere that
extends deep into the atmosphere, the nightside has no thermally driven ionosphere.
A corresponding asymmetry is imprinted in the ion and neutral composition at the
terminators. The ionosphere on HAT-P-7b may be directly traced by the Ca$^+$ H&amp;amp;K
lines if the local temperature is ensuremath≥5000 K. The whole atmosphere may
couple to a global, large-scale magnetic field, and lightning may occur on the
nightside.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Understanding the atmospheric properties and chemical composition of the ultra-hot Jupiter HAT-P-7b. II. Mapping the effects of gas kinetics</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publications/2020-aa-635-a-31-m.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publications/2020-aa-635-a-31-m.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Aims: The atmospheres of ultra-hot Jupiters (UHJs) are commonly considered
to be at thermochemical equilibrium. We aim to provide disequilibrium chemistry
maps for a global understanding of the chemistry in the atmosphere of HAT-P-7b and
assess the importance of disequilibrium chemistry on UHJs.  Methods: We applied
a hierarchical modeling approach using 97 1D atmospheric profiles from a 3D general
circulation model of HAT-P-7b. For each atmospheric 1D profile, we evaluated our
kinetic cloud formation model consistently with the local gas-phase composition
in chemical equilibrium. This served as input to study the quenching of dominating
CHNO- binding molecules. We evaluated quenching results from a zeroth- order approximation
in comparison to a kinetic gas-phase approach.  Results: We find that the zeroth-order
approach of estimating quenching points agrees well with the full gas-kinetic modeling
results. However, it underestimates the quenching levels by about one order of magnitude
at high temperatures. Chemical disequilibrium has the greatest effect on the nightside
and morning abundance of species such as H, H$_2$O, CH$_4$, CO$_2$, HCN, and all
C$_n$H$_m$ molecules; heavier C$_n$H$_m$ molecules are more affected by disequilibrium
processes. The CO abundance, however, is affected only marginally. While dayside
abundances also notably change, those around the evening terminator of HAT-P-7b
are the least affected by disequilibrium processes. The latter finding may partially
explain the consistency of observed transmission spectra of UHJs with atmospheres
in thermochemical equilibrium. Photochemistry only negligibly affects molecular
abundances and quenching levels.  Conclusions: In general, the quenching points
of the atmosphere of HAT-P-7b are at much lower pressures than in the cooler hot-jupiters.
We propose several avenues to determining the effect of disequilibrium processes
on UHJs that are in general based on abundance and opacity measurements at different
local times. It remains a challenge to completely disentangle this from the chemical
effects of clouds and that of a primordial nonsolar abundance.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Understanding the atmospheric properties and chemical composition of the ultra-hot Jupiter HAT-P-7b. I. Cloud and chemistry mapping</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publications/2019-aa-631-a-79-h.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publications/2019-aa-631-a-79-h.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Context. Of the presently known ensuremath≈3900 exoplanets, sparse spectral
observations are available for ensuremath≈100. Ultra-hot Jupiters have recently
attracted interest from observers and theoreticians alike, as they provide observationally
accessible test cases. Confronting detailed theoretical models with observations
is of preeminent importance in preparation for upcoming space-based telescopes.  Aims:
We aim to study cloud formation on the ultra-hot Jupiter HAT-P-7b, the resulting
composition of the local gas phase, and how their global changes affect wavelength-
dependent observations utilised to derive fundamental properties of the planet.  Methods:
We apply a hierarchical modelling approach as a virtual laboratory to study cloud
formation and gas-phase chemistry. We utilise 97 vertical 1D profiles of a 3D GCM
for HAT-P-7b to evaluate our kinetic cloud formation model consistently with the
local equilibrium gas- phase composition. We use maps and slice views to provide
a global understanding of the cloud and gas chemistry.  Results: The day/night temperature
difference on HAT-P-7b (ensuremathΔT ensuremath≈ 2500 K) causes clouds to form on
the nightside (dominated by H$_2$/He) while the dayside (dominated by H/He) retains
cloud-free equatorial regions. The cloud particles vary in composition and size
throughout the vertical extension of the cloud, but also globally. TiO$_2$[s]/Al$_2$O$_3$[s]/CaTiO$_3$[s]-particles
of cm- sized radii occur in the higher dayside-latitudes, resulting in a dayside
dominated by gas-phase opacity. The opacity on the nightside, however, is dominated
by 0.01textellipsis0.1ensuremathμm particles made of a material mix dominated by
silicates. The gas pressure at which the atmosphere becomes optically thick is 10$^-4$
bar in cloudy regions, and 0.1 bar in cloud-free regions.  Conclusions: HAT-P-7b
features strong morning/evening terminator asymmetries, providing an example of
patchy clouds and azimuthally-inhomogeneous chemistry. Variable terminator properties
may be accessible by ingress/egress transmission photometry (e.g., CHEOPS and PLATO)
or spectroscopy. The large temperature differences of ensuremath≈2500 K result in
an increasing geometrical extension from the night- to the dayside. The H$_2$O abundance
at the terminator changes by &amp;lt;1 dex with altitude and ensuremathłesssim0.3 dex (a
factor of 2) across the terminator for a given pressure, indicating that H$_2$O
abundances derived from transmission spectra can be representative of the well-mixed
metallicity at P ensuremathgtrsim 10 bar. We suggest the atmospheric C/O as an important
tool to trace the presence and location of clouds in exoplanet atmospheres. The
atmospheric C/O can be sub- and supersolar due to cloud formation. Phase curve variability
of HAT-P-7b is unlikely to be caused by dayside clouds.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The GTC exoplanet transit spectroscopy survey. VIII. Flat transmission spectrum for the warm gas giant WASP-80b</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publications/2018-aa-609-a-33-p.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publications/2018-aa-609-a-33-p.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Add the &lt;strong&gt;full text&lt;/strong&gt; or &lt;strong&gt;supplementary notes&lt;/strong&gt; for the publication here using Markdown formatting.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The GTC exoplanet transit spectroscopy survey . VII. An optical transmission spectrum of WASP-48b</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publications/2017-aa-605-a-114-m.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publications/2017-aa-605-a-114-m.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Add the &lt;strong&gt;full text&lt;/strong&gt; or &lt;strong&gt;supplementary notes&lt;/strong&gt; for the publication here using Markdown formatting.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The GTC exoplanet transit spectroscopy survey. IV. Confirmation of the flat transmission spectrum of HAT-P-32b</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publications/2016-aa-594-a-65-n.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publications/2016-aa-594-a-65-n.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Add the &lt;strong&gt;full text&lt;/strong&gt; or &lt;strong&gt;supplementary notes&lt;/strong&gt; for the publication here using Markdown formatting.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The GTC exoplanet transit spectroscopy survey. III. No asymmetries in the transit of CoRoT-29b</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publications/2016-aa-589-a-62-p.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 May 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publications/2016-aa-589-a-62-p.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Add the &lt;strong&gt;full text&lt;/strong&gt; or &lt;strong&gt;supplementary notes&lt;/strong&gt; for the publication here using Markdown formatting.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The GTC exoplanet transit spectroscopy survey. II. An overly large Rayleigh-like feature for exoplanet TrES-3b</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publications/2016-aa-585-a-114-p.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publications/2016-aa-585-a-114-p.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Add the &lt;strong&gt;full text&lt;/strong&gt; or &lt;strong&gt;supplementary notes&lt;/strong&gt; for the publication here using Markdown formatting.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Further Constraints on the Optical Transmission Spectrum of HAT-P-1b</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publications/2015-ap-j-811-55-m.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Sep 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publications/2015-ap-j-811-55-m.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Add the &lt;strong&gt;full text&lt;/strong&gt; or &lt;strong&gt;supplementary notes&lt;/strong&gt; for the publication here using Markdown formatting.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The atmospheric chemistry of the warm Neptune GJ 3470b: Influence of metallicity and temperature on the CH$_4$/CO ratio</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publications/2014-aa-562-a-51-v.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Feb 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publications/2014-aa-562-a-51-v.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Add the &lt;strong&gt;full text&lt;/strong&gt; or &lt;strong&gt;supplementary notes&lt;/strong&gt; for the publication here using Markdown formatting.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Puzzling Chemical Composition of GJ 436b&#39;s Atmosphere: Influence of Tidal Heating on the Chemistry</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publications/2014-ap-j-781-68-a.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Feb 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publications/2014-ap-j-781-68-a.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Add the &lt;strong&gt;full text&lt;/strong&gt; or &lt;strong&gt;supplementary notes&lt;/strong&gt; for the publication here using Markdown formatting.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Spitzer 3.6 and 4.5 ensuremathμm full-orbit light curves of WASP-18</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publications/2013-mnras-428-2645-m.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publications/2013-mnras-428-2645-m.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Add the &lt;strong&gt;full text&lt;/strong&gt; or &lt;strong&gt;supplementary notes&lt;/strong&gt; for the publication here using Markdown formatting.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The impact of atmospheric circulation on the chemistry of the hot Jupiter HD 209458b</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publications/2012-aa-548-a-73-a.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Dec 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publications/2012-aa-548-a-73-a.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Add the &lt;strong&gt;full text&lt;/strong&gt; or &lt;strong&gt;supplementary notes&lt;/strong&gt; for the publication here using Markdown formatting.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A chemical model for the atmosphere of hot Jupiters</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publications/2012-aa-546-a-43-v.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Oct 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publications/2012-aa-546-a-43-v.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Add the &lt;strong&gt;full text&lt;/strong&gt; or &lt;strong&gt;supplementary notes&lt;/strong&gt; for the publication here using Markdown formatting.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
