<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Mini Neptunes | Nicolas Iro</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/tag/mini-neptunes.html</link>
      <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/tag/mini-neptunes/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Mini Neptunes</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 01 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>http://localhost:1313/media/logo_hu_a8d074ae3d848875.png</url>
      <title>Mini Neptunes</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/tag/mini-neptunes.html</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>The CUISINES Framework for Conducting Exoplanet Model Intercomparison Projects, Version 1.0</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publications/2024-psj-5-175-s.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publications/2024-psj-5-175-s.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As JWST begins to return observations, it is more important than ever that
exoplanet climate models can consistently and correctly predict the observability
of exoplanets, retrieval of their data, and interpretation of planetary environments
from that data. Model intercomparisons play a crucial role in this context, especially
now when few data are available to validate model predictions. The CUISINES Working
Group of NASA&amp;rsquo;s Nexus for Exoplanet Systems Science supports a systematic approach
to evaluating the performance of exoplanet models and provides here a framework
for conducting community-organized exoplanet model intercomparison projects (exoMIPs).
The CUISINES framework adapts Earth climate community practices specifically for
the needs of the exoplanet researchers, encompassing a range of model types, planetary
targets, and parameter space studies. It is intended to help researchers to work
collectively, equitably, and openly toward common goals. The CUISINES framework
rests on five principles: (1) define in advance what research question(s) the
exoMIP is intended to address, (2) create an experimental design that maximizes
community participation and advertise it widely, (3) plan a project timeline that
allows all exoMIP members to participate fully, (4) generate data products from
model output for direct comparison to observations, and (5) create a data management
plan that is workable in the present and scalable for the future. Within the first
years of its existence, CUISINES is already providing logistical support to 10
exoMIPs and will continue to host annual workshops for further community feedback
and presentation of new exoMIP ideas.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
