<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Planets and Satellites: Terrestrial Planets | Nicolas Iro</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/tag/planets-and-satellites-terrestrial-planets.html</link>
      <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/tag/planets-and-satellites-terrestrial-planets/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Planets and Satellites: Terrestrial Planets</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>http://localhost:1313/media/logo_hu_a8d074ae3d848875.png</url>
      <title>Planets and Satellites: Terrestrial Planets</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/tag/planets-and-satellites-terrestrial-planets.html</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>The effect of a biosphere on the habitable timespan of stagnant-lid planets and implications for the atmospheric spectrum</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publications/2025-aa-693-a-205-h.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publications/2025-aa-693-a-205-h.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Temperature-dependent biological productivity controls silicate weathering
and thereby extends the potential habitable timespan of Earth. Models and theoretical
considerations indicate that the runaway greenhouse on Earth-like exoplanets is
generally accompanied by a dramatic increase in atmospheric H$_2$O and CO$_2$, which
might be observed with the upcoming generation of space telescopes. If an active
biosphere extends the habitable timespan of exoplanets similarly to Earth, observing
the atmospheric spectra of exoplanets near the inner edge of the habitable zone
could then give insights into whether the planet is inhabited. Here, we explore
this idea for Earth-like stagnant-lid planets. We find that while for a reduced
mantle, a surface biosphere extends the habitable timespan of the planet by about
1 Gyr, for more oxidising conditions, the biologically enhanced rate of weathering
becomes increasingly compensated for by an increased supply rate of CO$_2$ to the
atmosphere. Observationally, the resulting difference in atmospheric CO$_2$ near
the inner edge of the habitable zone is clearly distinguishable between biotic planets
with active weathering and abiotic planets that have experienced a runaway greenhouse.
For an efficient hydrological cycle, the increased bioproductivity also leads to
a CH$_4$ biosignature observable with JWST. As the planet becomes uninhabitable,
the H$_2$O infrared absorption bands dominate, but the 4.3-textmum CO$_2$ band remains
a clear window into the CO$_2$ abundances. In summary, while the effect of life
on the carbonate-silicate cycle leaves a record in the atmospheric spectrum of Earth-like
stagnant-lid planets, future work is needed especially to determine the tectonic
state and composition of exoplanets and to push forward the development of the next
generation of space telescopes.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
