<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Nicolas Iro</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/index.html</link>
      <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Nicolas Iro</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 01 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>http://localhost:1313/media/logo_hu_a8d074ae3d848875.png</url>
      <title>Nicolas Iro</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/index.html</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>PhD in Astrophysics</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/cv/1_phd.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/cv/1_phd.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;i class=&#34;fas fa-graduation-cap  pr-1 fa-fw&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; University Paris VI, 2005.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Master in Astrophysics</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/cv/0_master.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/cv/0_master.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;i class=&#34;fas fa-graduation-cap  pr-1 fa-fw&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; University Paris VI, 2001.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Postdoctoral Researcher 2022--2025</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/cv/dlr.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/cv/dlr.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
   &lt;i class=&#34;fas fa-globe  pr-1 fa-fw&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;  Institute for Planetary Research - German Aerospace Center (DLR), Berlin, DE.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;INCREASE (INfluence of strong stellar particle event and galactic Cosmic Rays on Exoplanetary AtmoSpherEs), Contact: J. L. Grenfell.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tasks:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Studying the effect of energetic particles on the atmospheres of exoplanets.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Adding new features to the 1D climate model 1D-TERRA.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Migrating it from SVN to git framework.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Participating in international consortia such as Cheops, PLATO, ARIEL, JWST.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Leading an intercomparison effort for hot Jupiter climate models.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Postdoctoral Researcher 2017--2022</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/cv/vienna.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/cv/vienna.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;i class=&#34;fas fa-globe  pr-1 fa-fw&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; Astrophysics Department - University of Vienna, Austria.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pathways to Habitability, Contact: M. Güdel&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tasks:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Using a hierarchy of models in order to study planetary atmospheres and habitability:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1D radiative transfer (to be combined with upper atmosphere),&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;3D radiative transfer (PHOENIX)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;3D General Circulation Model (Plasim / PUMA)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Teaching&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Postdoctoral Researcher 2012--2027</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/cv/hamburg.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/cv/hamburg.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
   &lt;i class=&#34;fas fa-globe  pr-1 fa-fw&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;  Theoretical Meteorology Group, Klimacampus - University of Hamburg, Germany.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Planetary Atmospheres research, Contact: V. Lucarini&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tasks:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Expending the expertise of the Group by developing a new Planetary Atmosphere division.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Studying the diverse radiation and circulation regimes of exoplanets - from Hot Jupiters to Earth-like planets.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Responsible of modifying the radiative transfer schemes in the PlanetSimulator and PUMA exoplanets GCM codes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>JWST WASP-18b multidimensional mapping</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/news/jwst-mapping.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/news/jwst-mapping.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Two-dimensional maps from the Eigenspectra method for each of the 25 spectroscopic bins.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://media.springernature.com/full/springer-static/image/art%3A10.1038%2Fs41550-025-02666-9/MediaObjects/41550_2025_2666_Fig1_HTML.png?as=webp&#34; alt=&#34;alt&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See the &lt;a href=&#34;./publications/2025-ar-xiv-251024708-c.html&#34;&gt;Article&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Horizontal and vertical exoplanet thermal structure from a JWST spectroscopic eclipse map</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publications/2025-ar-xiv-251024708-c.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publications/2025-ar-xiv-251024708-c.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Highly-irradiated giant exoplanets known as &amp;lsquo;&amp;lsquo;ultra-hot Jupiters&amp;rsquo;&amp;rsquo; are
anticipated to exhibit large variations of atmospheric temperature and chemistry
as a function of longitude, latitude, and altitude. Previous observations have
hinted at these variations, but the existing data have been fundamentally restricted
to probing hemisphere-integrated spectra, thereby providing only coarse information
on atmospheric gradients. Here we present a spectroscopic eclipse map of an extrasolar
planet, resolving the atmosphere in multiple dimensions simultaneously. We analyze
a secondary eclipse of the ultra-hot Jupiter WASP-18b observed with the NIRISS
instrument on JWST. The mapping reveals weaker longitudinal temperature gradients
than were predicted by theoretical models, indicating the importance of hydrogen
dissociation and/or nightside clouds in shaping global thermal emission. Additionally,
we identify two thermally distinct regions of the planet&amp;rsquo;s atmosphere: a &amp;lsquo;&amp;lsquo;hotspot&amp;rsquo;&amp;rsquo;
surrounding the substellar point and a &amp;ldquo;ring&amp;rdquo; near the dayside limbs. The hotspot
region shows a strongly inverted thermal structure due to the presence of optical
absorbers and a water abundance marginally lower than the hemispheric average,
in accordance with theoretical predictions. The ring region shows colder temperatures
and poorly constrained chemical abundances. Similar future analyses will reveal
three-dimensional thermal, chemical, and dynamical properties of a broad range
of exoplanet atmospheres.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cheops WASP-18b phase curve</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/news/cheops-wasp-18b.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Sep 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/news/cheops-wasp-18b.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHEOPS phase-folded phase curve.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://www.aanda.org/articles/aa/full_html/2025/07/aa50939-24/aa50939-24-fig2.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;alt&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See the &lt;a href=&#34;./publications/2025-aa-699-a-150-d.html&#34;&gt;Article&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Climate modelling</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/research/gcm.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Sep 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/research/gcm.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;With the first JWST data already available, and ARIEL in the near future, we are expecting to get a lot of time-varying measurements of exoplanets (e.g. phase curves and 3D eclipse maps), giving us unprecedented information about their climate. Hot Jupiters will be the best targets for atmosphere characterisation with these facilities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;3D atmospheric circulation models are the main tools to interpret theoretically these upcoming observations. However, various models have been developed, with  different assumptions and setup. Some characteristics of the outputs are then dependent on the model used, impairing physical interpretation. It is therefore necessary to assess the differences, limits and applicability of each model.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am leading the first extensive and systematic intercomparision of hot Jupiter 3D circulation models. Our team is built from the experts developing all available codes,  in order to set up a common benchmark methodology. Our intercomparison project will provide the exoplanet community with better and more robust tools to retrieve physical information from JWST data, and later ARIEL.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>First JWST thermal phase curves of temperate terrestrial exoplanets reveal no thick atmosphere around TRAPPIST-1 b and c</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publications/2025-ar-xiv-250902128-g.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Sep 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publications/2025-ar-xiv-250902128-g.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We report JWST/MIRI 15 μm phase curves of TRAPPIST-1 b and c, revealing
thermal emission consistent with their irradiation levels, assuming no efficient
heat redistribution. We find that TRAPPIST-1 b shows a high dayside brightness temperature
(490 ± 17 K), no significantly detectable nightside emission (F[b, Night,
max] = 39_-27^+55 ppm), and no phase offset &amp;ndash; features consistent with a low-albedo,
airless ultramafic rocky surface. TRAPPIST-1 c exhibits a lower dayside brightness
temperature (369 ± 23 K), and a nightside flux statistically indistinguishable
from that of TRAPPIST-1 b (F[c, Night, max] = 62_-43^+60 ppm). Atmosphere models
with surface pressures $≥$1 bar and efficient greenhouse effects are strongly disfavoured
for both planets. TRAPPIST-1 b is unlikely to possess any substantial atmosphere,
while TRAPPIST-1 c may retain a tenuous, greenhouse-poor O$_2$-dominated atmosphere
or be similarly airless with a more reflective surface. These results suggest divergent
evolutionary pathways or atmospheric loss processes, despite similar compositions.
These measurements tightly constrain atmosphere retention in the inner TRAPPIST-1
system.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>JWST</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/research/jwst.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Sep 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/research/jwst.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;JWST summary&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Limb Asymmetries on WASP-39b: A Multi-GCM Comparison of Chemistry, Clouds, and Hazes</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publications/2025-ar-xiv-250921588-s.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Sep 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publications/2025-ar-xiv-250921588-s.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;With JWST, observing separate spectra of the morning and evening limbs of
hot Jupiters has finally become a reality. The first such observation was reported
for WASP-39b, where the evening terminator was observed to have a larger transit
radius by about 400 ppm and a stronger 4.3 μm CO2 feature than the morning
terminator. Multiple factors, including temperature differences, photo/thermochemistry,
clouds and hazes, could cause such limb asymmetries. To interpret these new limb
asymmetry observations, a detailed understanding of how the relevant processes affect
morning and evening spectra grounded in forward models is needed. Focusing on WASP-39b,
we compare simulations from five different general circulation models (GCMs), including
one simulating disequilibrium thermochemistry and one with cloud radiative feedback,
to the recent WASP-39b limb asymmetry observations. We also post-process the temperature
structures of all simulations with a 2D photochemical model and one simulation with
a cloud microphysics model. Although the temperatures predicted by the different
models vary considerably, the models are remarkably consistent in their predicted
morning&amp;ndash;evening temperature differences. Several equilibrium-chemistry simulations
predict strong methane features in the morning spectrum, not seen in the observations.
When including disequilibrium processes, horizontal transport homogenizes methane,
and these methane features disappear. However, even after including photochemistry
and clouds, our models still cannot reproduce the observed ∼2000 ppm asymmetry
in the CO2 feature. A combination of factors, such as varying metallicity and
unexplored parameters in cloud models, may explain the discrepancy, emphasizing
the need for future models integrating cloud microphysics and feedback across a
broader parameter space.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ARIEL</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/research/ariel.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Aug 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/research/ariel.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Cheops is the first small class mission satellite from ESA.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Astrophotography</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hobbies/astrophoto-1.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Aug 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hobbies/astrophoto-1.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Latest attempt at a picture of the Moon.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cheops</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/research/cheops.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Aug 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/research/cheops.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Cheops is the first small class mission satellite from ESA.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Landscape</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hobbies/photo2.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Aug 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hobbies/photo2.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Landscape picture. Les Houches (France), 2023&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Nature</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hobbies/photo1a.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Aug 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hobbies/photo1a.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Nature picture.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Nature</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hobbies/photo1b.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Aug 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hobbies/photo1b.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Nature picture.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dark skies of the slightly eccentric WASP-18 b from its optical-to-infrared dayside emission</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publications/2025-aa-699-a-150-d.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jul 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publications/2025-aa-699-a-150-d.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Context. Ultra-hot Jupiters (UHJs) are gas giant exoplanets that are strongly
irradiated by their star, setting intense molecular dissociation that leads to atmospheric
chemistry dominated by ions and atoms. These conditions inhibit day-to-night heat
redistribution, which results in high temperature contrasts. Phase-curve observations
over several passbands offer insights on the thermal structure and properties of
these extreme atmospheres. Aims. We aim to perform a joint analysis of multiple
observations of WASP-18 b from the visible to the mid- infrared, using data from
CHEOPS, TESS, and Spitzer. Our purpose is to characterise the planetary atmosphere
with a consistent view over the large wavelength range covered, including JWST data.
Methods. We implemented a model for the planetary signal including transits, occultations,
phase signal, ellipsoidal variations, Doppler boosting, and light travel time. We
performed a joint fit of more than 250 eclipse events and derived the atmospheric
properties using general circulation models (GCMs) and retrieval analyses. Results.
We obtained new ephemerides with unprecedented precisions of 1 second and 1.4 millisecond
on the time of inferior conjunction and orbital period, respectively. We computed
a planetary radius of R $_ p $ = 1.1926 ensuremath± 0.0077 R $_ J $ with a precision
of 0.65% (or 550 km). Based on a timing inconsistency with JWST, we discuss and
confirm the orbital eccentricity (e = 0.00852 ensuremath± 0.00091). We also constrain
the argument of periastron to ensuremathømega = 261.9$_‑1.4$ $^+1.3$ deg. We show
that the large dayside emission implies the presence of magnetic drag and super-solar
metallicity. We find a steep thermally inverted gradient in the planetary atmosphere,
which is common for UHJs. We detected the presence of strong CO emission lines at
4.5 ensuremathμm from an excess of dayside brightness in the Spitzer/IRAC/Channel
2 passband. Using these models to constrain the reflected contribution in the CHEOPS
passband, we derived an extremely low geometric albedo of A$_g$ $^CHEOPS$ = 0.027
ensuremath± 0.011. Conclusions. The orbital eccentricity remains a potential challenge
for planetary dynamics that might require further study given the short-period massive
planet and despite the young age of the system. The characterisation of the atmosphere
of WASP-18 b reveals the necessity to account for magnetic friction and super-solar
metallicity to explain the full picture of the dayside emission. We find the planetary
dayside to be extremely unreflective; however, when juxtaposing TESS and CHEOPS
data, we get hints of increased scattering efficiency in the visible, likely due
to Rayleigh scattering.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The PLATO mission</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publications/2025-ex-a-59-26-r.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jun 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publications/2025-ex-a-59-26-r.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;PLATO (PLAnetary Transits and Oscillations of stars) is ESA&amp;rsquo;s M3 mission
designed to detect and characterise extrasolar planets and perform asteroseismic
monitoring of a large number of stars. PLATO will detect small planets (down to
&amp;lt;2REarth) around bright stars (&amp;lt;11 mag), including terrestrial planets in the habitable
zone of solar-like stars. With the complement of radial velocity observations from
the ground, planets will be characterised for their radius, mass, and age with high
accuracy (5%, 10%, 10% for an Earth-Sun combination respectively). PLATO will provide
us with a large-scale catalogue of well-characterised small planets up to intermediate
orbital periods, relevant for a meaningful comparison to planet formation theories
and to better understand planet evolution. It will make possible comparative exoplanetology
to place our Solar System planets in a broader context. In parallel, PLATO will
study (host) stars using asteroseismology, allowing us to determine the stellar
properties with high accuracy, substantially enhancing our knowledge of stellar
structure and evolution. The payload instrument consists of 26 cameras with 12cm
aperture each. For at least four years, the mission will perform high-precision
photometric measurements. Here we review the science objectives, present PLATO&amp;rsquo;s
target samples and fields, provide an overview of expected core science performance
as well as a description of the instrument and the mission profile towards the end
of the serial production of the flight cameras. PLATO is scheduled for a launch
date end 2026. This overview therefore provides a summary of the mission to the
community in preparation of the upcoming operational phases.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The effect of a biosphere on the habitable timespan of stagnant-lid planets and implications for the atmospheric spectrum</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publications/2025-aa-693-a-205-h.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publications/2025-aa-693-a-205-h.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Temperature-dependent biological productivity controls silicate weathering
and thereby extends the potential habitable timespan of Earth. Models and theoretical
considerations indicate that the runaway greenhouse on Earth-like exoplanets is
generally accompanied by a dramatic increase in atmospheric H$_2$O and CO$_2$, which
might be observed with the upcoming generation of space telescopes. If an active
biosphere extends the habitable timespan of exoplanets similarly to Earth, observing
the atmospheric spectra of exoplanets near the inner edge of the habitable zone
could then give insights into whether the planet is inhabited. Here, we explore
this idea for Earth-like stagnant-lid planets. We find that while for a reduced
mantle, a surface biosphere extends the habitable timespan of the planet by about
1 Gyr, for more oxidising conditions, the biologically enhanced rate of weathering
becomes increasingly compensated for by an increased supply rate of CO$_2$ to the
atmosphere. Observationally, the resulting difference in atmospheric CO$_2$ near
the inner edge of the habitable zone is clearly distinguishable between biotic planets
with active weathering and abiotic planets that have experienced a runaway greenhouse.
For an efficient hydrological cycle, the increased bioproductivity also leads to
a CH$_4$ biosignature observable with JWST. As the planet becomes uninhabitable,
the H$_2$O infrared absorption bands dominate, but the 4.3-textmum CO$_2$ band remains
a clear window into the CO$_2$ abundances. In summary, while the effect of life
on the carbonate-silicate cycle leaves a record in the atmospheric spectrum of Earth-like
stagnant-lid planets, future work is needed especially to determine the tectonic
state and composition of exoplanets and to push forward the development of the next
generation of space telescopes.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The CUISINES Framework for Conducting Exoplanet Model Intercomparison Projects, Version 1.0</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publications/2024-psj-5-175-s.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publications/2024-psj-5-175-s.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As JWST begins to return observations, it is more important than ever that
exoplanet climate models can consistently and correctly predict the observability
of exoplanets, retrieval of their data, and interpretation of planetary environments
from that data. Model intercomparisons play a crucial role in this context, especially
now when few data are available to validate model predictions. The CUISINES Working
Group of NASA&amp;rsquo;s Nexus for Exoplanet Systems Science supports a systematic approach
to evaluating the performance of exoplanet models and provides here a framework
for conducting community-organized exoplanet model intercomparison projects (exoMIPs).
The CUISINES framework adapts Earth climate community practices specifically for
the needs of the exoplanet researchers, encompassing a range of model types, planetary
targets, and parameter space studies. It is intended to help researchers to work
collectively, equitably, and openly toward common goals. The CUISINES framework
rests on five principles: (1) define in advance what research question(s) the
exoMIP is intended to address, (2) create an experimental design that maximizes
community participation and advertise it widely, (3) plan a project timeline that
allows all exoMIP members to participate fully, (4) generate data products from
model output for direct comparison to observations, and (5) create a data management
plan that is workable in the present and scalable for the future. Within the first
years of its existence, CUISINES is already providing logistical support to 10
exoMIPs and will continue to host annual workshops for further community feedback
and presentation of new exoMIP ideas.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A roadmap for the atmospheric characterization of terrestrial exoplanets with JWST</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publications/2024-nat-as-8-810-t.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publications/2024-nat-as-8-810-t.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Ultracool dwarf stars are abundant, long-lived and uniquely suited to enable
the atmospheric study of transiting terrestrial companions with the JWST. Among
them, the most prominent is the M8.5V star TRAPPIST-1 and its seven planets. While
JWST Cycle 1 observations have started to yield preliminary insights into the planets,
they have also revealed that their atmospheric exploration requires a better understanding
of their host star. Here we propose a roadmap to characterize the TRAPPIST-1 system
— and others like it — in an efficient and robust manner with JWST. We notably recommend
that — although more challenging to schedule — multi-transit windows be prioritized
to mitigate the effects of stellar activity and gather up to twice more transits
per JWST hour spent. We conclude that, for such systems, planets cannot be studied
in isolation by small programmes but rather need large-scale, joint space- and ground-
based initiatives to fully exploit the capabilities of JWST for the exploration
of terrestrial planets.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Nightside clouds and disequilibrium chemistry on the hot Jupiter WASP-43b</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publications/2024-nat-as-8-879-b.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publications/2024-nat-as-8-879-b.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Hot Jupiters are among the best-studied exoplanets, but it is still poorly
understood how their chemical composition and cloud properties vary with longitude.
Theoretical models predict that clouds may condense on the nightside and that molecular
abundances can be driven out of equilibrium by zonal winds. Here we report a phase-resolved
emission spectrum of the hot Jupiter WASP-43b measured from 5 ensuremathμm to 12
ensuremathμm with the JWST&amp;rsquo;s Mid-Infrared Instrument. The spectra reveal a large
day-night temperature contrast (with average brightness temperatures of 1,524 ensuremath±
35 K and 863 ensuremath± 23 K, respectively) and evidence for water absorption at
all orbital phases. Comparisons with three- dimensional atmospheric models show
that both the phase-curve shape and emission spectra strongly suggest the presence
of nightside clouds that become optically thick to thermal emission at pressures
greater than åisebox-0.5ex~100 mbar. The dayside is consistent with a cloudless
atmosphere above the mid-infrared photosphere. Contrary to expectations from equilibrium
chemistry but consistent with disequilibrium kinetics models, methane is not detected
on the nightside (2ensuremathσ upper limit of 1-6 ppm, depending on model assumptions).
Our results provide strong evidence that the atmosphere of WASP-43b is shaped by
disequilibrium processes and provide new insights into the properties of the planet&amp;rsquo;s
nightside clouds. However, the remaining discrepancies between our observations
and our predictive atmospheric models emphasize the importance of further exploring
the effects of clouds and disequilibrium chemistry in numerical models.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Impact of Cosmic Rays on Atmospheric Ion Chemistry and Spectral Transmission Features of TRAPPIST-1e</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publications/2024-ap-j-961-164-h.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Feb 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publications/2024-ap-j-961-164-h.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Ongoing observing projects like the James Webb Space Telescope and future
missions offer the chance to characterize Earth-like exoplanetary atmospheres. Thereby,
M dwarfs are preferred targets for transit observations, for example, due to their
favorable planet–star contrast ratio. However, the radiation and particle environment
of these cool stars could be far more extreme than what we know from the Sun. Thus,
knowing the stellar radiation and particle environment and its possible influence
on detectable biosignatures—in particular, signs of life like ozone and methane—is
crucial to understanding upcoming transit spectra. In this study, with the help
of our unique model suite INCREASE, we investigate the impact of a strong stellar
energetic particle event on the atmospheric ionization, neutral and ion chemistry,
and atmospheric biosignatures of TRAPPIST-1e. Therefore, transit spectra for six
scenarios are simulated. We find that a Carrington-like event drastically increases
atmospheric ionization and induces substantial changes in ion chemistry and spectral
transmission features: all scenarios show high event- induced amounts of nitrogen
dioxide (i.e., at 6.2 ensuremathμm), a reduction of the atmospheric transit depth
in all water bands (i.e., at 5.5–7.0 ensuremathμm), a decrease of the methane bands
(i.e., at 3.0–3.5 ensuremathμm), and depletion of ozone (i.e., at ensuremath∼9.6
ensuremathμm). Therefore, it is essential to include high-energy particle effects
to correctly assign biosignature signals from, e.g., ozone and methane. We further
show that the nitric acid feature at 11.0–12.0 ensuremathμm, discussed as a proxy
for stellar particle contamination, is absent in wet-dead atmospheres.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sulfur dioxide in the mid-infrared transmission spectrum of WASP-39b</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publications/2024-natur-626-979-p.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Feb 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publications/2024-natur-626-979-p.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The recent inference of sulfur dioxide (SO$_2$) in the atmosphere of the
hot (approximately 1,100 K), Saturn-mass exoplanet WASP-39b from near-infrared JWST
observations$^1-3$ suggests that photochemistry is a key process in high-temperature
exoplanet atmospheres$^4$. This is because of the low (&amp;lt;1 ppb) abundance of SO$_2$
under thermochemical equilibrium compared with that produced from the photochemistry
of H$_2$O and H$_2$S (1-10 ppm)$^4-9$. However, the SO$_2$ inference was made from
a single, small molecular feature in the transmission spectrum of WASP-39b at 4.05
ensuremathμm and, therefore, the detection of other SO$_2$ absorption bands at different
wavelengths is needed to better constrain the SO$_2$ abundance. Here we report the
detection of SO$_2$ spectral features at 7.7 and 8.5 ensuremathμm in the 5-12-ensuremathμm
transmission spectrum of WASP-39b measured by the JWST Mid-Infrared Instrument (MIRI)
Low Resolution Spectrometer (LRS)$^10$. Our observations suggest an abundance of
SO$_2$ of 0.5-25 ppm (1ensuremathσ range), consistent with previous findings$^4$.
As well as SO$_2$, we find broad water-vapour absorption features, as well as an
unexplained decrease in the transit depth at wavelengths longer than 10 ensuremathμm.
Fitting the spectrum with a grid of atmospheric forward models, we derive an atmospheric
heavy-element content (metallicity) for WASP-39b of approximately 7.1-8.0 times
solar and demonstrate that photochemistry shapes the spectra of WASP-39b across
a broad wavelength range.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A broadband thermal emission spectrum of the ultra-hot Jupiter WASP-18b</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publications/2023-natur-620-292-c.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Aug 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publications/2023-natur-620-292-c.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Close-in giant exoplanets with temperatures greater than 2,000 K (&amp;lsquo;ultra-hot
Jupiters&amp;rsquo;) have been the subject of extensive efforts to determine their atmospheric
properties using thermal emission measurements from the Hubble Space Telescope (HST)
and Spitzer Space Telescope$^1-3$. However, previous studies have yielded inconsistent
results because the small sizes of the spectral features and the limited information
content of the data resulted in high sensitivity to the varying assumptions made
in the treatment of instrument systematics and the atmospheric retrieval analysis$^3-12$.
Here we present a dayside thermal emission spectrum of the ultra-hot Jupiter WASP-18b
obtained with the NIRISS$^13$ instrument on the JWST. The data span 0.85 to 2.85
ensuremathμm in wavelength at an average resolving power of 400 and exhibit minimal
systematics. The spectrum shows three water emission features (at &amp;gt;6σ
confidence) and evidence for optical opacity, possibly attributable to H$^-$,
TiO and VO (combined significance of 3.8σ). Models that fit the data require
a thermal inversion, molecular dissociation as predicted by chemical equilibrium,
a solar heavy-element abundance (&amp;lsquo;metallicity&amp;rsquo;, M/H =1.0 3$_-0.51$$^+1.11$
times solar) and a carbon- to-oxygen (C/O) ratio less than unity. The data also
yield a dayside brightness temperature map, which shows a peak in temperature near
the substellar point that decreases steeply and symmetrically with longitude towards
the terminators.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Detection of Carbon Monoxide&#39;s 4.6 Micron Fundamental Band Structure in WASP-39b&#39;s Atmosphere with JWST NIRSpec G395H</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publications/2023-ap-j-949-l-15-g.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publications/2023-ap-j-949-l-15-g.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Carbon monoxide (CO) is predicted to be the dominant carbon-bearing molecule
in giant planet atmospheres and, along with water, is important for discerning the
oxygen and therefore carbon-to- oxygen ratio of these planets. The fundamental absorption
mode of CO has a broad, double-branched structure composed of many individual absorption
lines from 4.3 to 5.1 ensuremathμm, which can now be spectroscopically measured
with JWST. Here we present a technique for detecting the rotational sub-band structure
of CO at medium resolution with the NIRSpec G395H instrument. We use a single transit
observation of the hot Jupiter WASP-39b from the JWST Transiting Exoplanet Community
Early Release Science (JTEC ERS) program at the native resolution of the instrument
(R åisebox-0.5ex~ 2700) to resolve the CO absorption structure. We robustly detect
absorption by CO, with an increase in transit depth of 264 ensuremath± 68 ppm, in
agreement with the predicted CO contribution from the best-fit model at low resolution.
This detection confirms our theoretical expectations that CO is the dominant carbon-bearing
molecule in WASP-39b&amp;rsquo;s atmosphere and further supports the conclusions of low C/O
and supersolar metallicities presented in the JTEC ERS papers for WASP-39b.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Early Release Science of the exoplanet WASP-39b with JWST NIRCam</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publications/2023-natur-614-653-a.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publications/2023-natur-614-653-a.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Measuring the metallicity and carbon-to-oxygen (C/O) ratio in exoplanet
atmospheres is a fundamental step towards constraining the dominant chemical processes
at work and, if in equilibrium, revealing planet formation histories. Transmission
spectroscopy (for example, refs. $^1,2$) provides the necessary means by constraining
the abundances of oxygen- and carbon-bearing species; however, this requires broad
wavelength coverage, moderate spectral resolution and high precision, which, together,
are not achievable with previous observatories. Now that JWST has commenced science
operations, we are able to observe exoplanets at previously uncharted wavelengths
and spectral resolutions. Here we report time-series observations of the transiting
exoplanet WASP-39b using JWST&amp;rsquo;s Near InfraRed Camera (NIRCam). The long-wavelength
spectroscopic and short- wavelength photometric light curves span 2.0-4.0 micrometres,
exhibit minimal systematics and reveal well defined molecular absorption features
in the planet&amp;rsquo;s spectrum. Specifically, we detect gaseous water in the atmosphere
and place an upper limit on the abundance of methane. The otherwise prominent carbon
dioxide feature at 2.8 micrometres is largely masked by water. The best-fit chemical
equilibrium models favour an atmospheric metallicity of 1-100-times solar (that
is, an enrichment of elements heavier than helium relative to the Sun) and a substellar
C/O ratio. The inferred high metallicity and low C/O ratio may indicate significant
accretion of solid materials during planet formation (for example, refs. $^3,4$$^,$)
or disequilibrium processes in the upper atmosphere (for example, refs. $^5,6$).&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Early Release Science of the exoplanet WASP-39b with JWST NIRISS</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publications/2023-natur-614-670-f.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publications/2023-natur-614-670-f.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The Saturn-mass exoplanet WASP-39b has been the subject of extensive efforts
to determine its atmospheric properties using transmission spectroscopy$^1-4$. However,
these efforts have been hampered by modelling degeneracies between composition and
cloud properties that are caused by limited data quality$^5-9$. Here we present
the transmission spectrum of WASP-39b obtained using the Single-Object Slitless
Spectroscopy (SOSS) mode of the Near Infrared Imager and Slitless Spectrograph (NIRISS)
instrument on the JWST. This spectrum spans 0.6-2.8 ensuremathμm in wavelength and
shows several water-absorption bands, the potassium resonance doublet and signatures
of clouds. The precision and broad wavelength coverage of NIRISS/SOSS allows us
to break model degeneracies between cloud properties and the atmospheric composition
of WASP-39b, favouring a heavy-element enhancement (`metallicity&amp;rsquo;) of about 10-30
times the solar value, a sub-solar carbon-to- oxygen (C/O) ratio and a solar-to-super-solar
potassium-to- oxygen (K/O) ratio. The observations are also best explained by wavelength-dependent,
non-grey clouds with inhomogeneous coverageof the planet&amp;rsquo;s terminator.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Early Release Science of the exoplanet WASP-39b with JWST NIRSpec G395H</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publications/2023-natur-614-664-a.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publications/2023-natur-614-664-a.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Measuring the abundances of carbon and oxygen in exoplanet atmospheres is
considered a crucial avenue for unlocking the formation and evolution of exoplanetary
systems$^1,2$. Access to the chemical inventory of an exoplanet requires high-precision
observations, often inferred from individual molecular detections with low-resolution
space-based$^3-5$ and high- resolution ground-based$^6-8$ facilities. Here we report
the medium-resolution (R ensuremath≈ 600) transmission spectrum of an exoplanet
atmosphere between 3 and 5 ensuremathμm covering several absorption features for
the Saturn-mass exoplanet WASP-39b (ref. $^9$), obtained with the Near Infrared
Spectrograph (NIRSpec) G395H grating of JWST. Our observations achieve 1.46 times
photon precision, providing an average transit depth uncertainty of 221 ppm per
spectroscopic bin, and present minimal impacts from systematic effects. We detect
significant absorption from CO$_2$ (28.5ensuremathσ) and H$_2$O (21.5ensuremathσ),
and identify SO$_2$ as the source of absorption at 4.1 ensuremathμm (4.8ensuremathσ).
Best-fit atmospheric models range between 3 and 10 times solar metallicity, with
sub-solar to solar C/O ratios. These results, including the detection of SO$_2$,
underscore the importance of characterizing the chemistry in exoplanet atmospheres
and showcase NIRSpec G395H as an excellent mode for time-series observations over
this critical wavelength range$^10$.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Early Release Science of the exoplanet WASP-39b with JWST NIRSpec PRISM</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publications/2023-natur-614-659-r.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publications/2023-natur-614-659-r.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Transmission spectroscopy$^1-3$ of exoplanets has revealed signatures of
water vapour, aerosols and alkali metals in a few dozen exoplanet atmospheres$^4,5$.
However, these previous inferences with the Hubble and Spitzer Space Telescopes
were hindered by the observations&amp;rsquo; relatively narrow wavelength range and spectral
resolving power, which precluded the unambiguous identification of other chemical
species—in particular the primary carbon-bearing molecules$^6,7$. Here we report
a broad-wavelength 0.5-5.5 textmum atmospheric transmission spectrum of WASP-39b$^8$,
a 1,200 K, roughly Saturn-mass, Jupiter-radius exoplanet, measured with the JWST
NIRSpec&amp;rsquo;s PRISM mode$^9$ as part of the JWST Transiting Exoplanet Community Early
Release Science Team Program$^10-12$. We robustly detect several chemical species
at high significance, including Na (19σ), H$_2$O (33σ), CO$_2$
(28σ) and CO (7σ). The non-detection of CH$_4$, combined with
a strong CO$_2$ feature, favours atmospheric models with a super-solar atmospheric
metallicity. An unanticipated absorption feature at 4 textmum is best explained
by SO$_2$ (2.7σ), which could be a tracer of atmospheric photochemistry.
These observations demonstrate JWST&amp;rsquo;s sensitivity to a rich diversity of exoplanet
compositions and chemical processes.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Identification of carbon dioxide in an exoplanet atmosphere</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publications/2023-natur-614-649-j.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publications/2023-natur-614-649-j.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Carbon dioxide (CO$_2$) is a key chemical species that is found in a wide
range of planetary atmospheres. In the context of exoplanets, CO$_2$ is an indicator
of the metal enrichment (that is, elements heavier than helium, also called `metallicity&amp;rsquo;)$^1-3$,
and thus the formation processes of the primary atmospheres of hot gas giants$^4-6$.
It is also one of the most promising species to detect in the secondary atmospheres
of terrestrial exoplanets$^7-9$. Previous photometric measurements of transiting
planets with the Spitzer Space Telescope have given hints of the presence of CO$_2$,
but have not yielded definitive detections owing to the lack of unambiguous spectroscopic
identification$^10-12$. Here we present the detection of CO$_2$ in the atmosphere
of the gas giant exoplanet WASP-39b from transmission spectroscopy observations
obtained with JWST as part of the Early Release Science programme$^13,14$. The data
used in this study span 3.0-5.5 micrometres in wavelength and show a prominent CO$_2$
absorption feature at 4.3 micrometres (26-sigma significance). The overall spectrum
is well matched by one-dimensional, ten- times solar metallicity models that assume
radiative-convective- thermochemical equilibrium and have moderate cloud opacity.
These models predict that the atmosphere should have water, carbon monoxide and
hydrogen sulfide in addition to CO$_2$, but little methane. Furthermore, we also
tentatively detect a small absorption feature near 4.0 micrometres that is not reproduced
by these models.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Understanding the atmospheric properties and chemical composition of the ultra-hot Jupiter HAT-P-7b. III. Changing ionisation and the emergence of an ionosphere</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publications/2021-aa-648-a-80-h.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publications/2021-aa-648-a-80-h.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Context. Ultra-hot Jupiters are the hottest exoplanets that have been discovered
so far. They present a unique possibility to explore hot and cold chemistry on
one object. The tidally locked ultra- hot Jupiter HAT-P-7b has a day-to-night
temperature difference of ≃2500 K, confining cloud formation to the nightside
and efficient ionisation to the dayside. Both have distinct observational signatures.
Aims: We analyse plasma and magnetic processes in the atmosphere of the ultra-hot
Jupiter HAT-P-7b to investigate the formation of an ionosphere and the possibility
of magnetically coupling the atmospheric gas as the base for an extended exosphere.
We show which ions and atoms may be used as spectral tracers, and if and where
conditions for lightning may occur within the clouds of HAT-P-7b.  Methods: We
used 3D modelling results as input for a kinetic cloud formation code and evaluated
characteristic plasma and magnetic coupling parameters. A local thermodynamical
equilibrium radiative transfer was solved for the ionised gas phase. This study&lt;br&gt;
is confined to thermal ionisation only.  Results: The ionisation throughout HAT-P-7b&amp;rsquo;s
atmosphere varies drastically between day- and nightside. The dayside has high
levels of thermal ionisation and long-range electromagnetic interactions dominate
over kinetic electron-neutral interactions, suggesting a day-night difference
in magnetic coupling. K$^+$, Na$^+$, Li$^+$, Ca$^+$, and Al$^+$ are more abundant
than their atomic counterparts on the dayside. The minimum magnetic flux density
for electrons for magnetic coupling is B &amp;lt; 0.5 G for all regions of HAT-P-7b&amp;rsquo;s
atmosphere.  Conclusions: HAT-P-7b&amp;rsquo;s dayside has an asymmetric ionosphere that
extends deep into the atmosphere, the nightside has no thermally driven ionosphere.
A corresponding asymmetry is imprinted in the ion and neutral composition at the
terminators. The ionosphere on HAT-P-7b may be directly traced by the Ca$^+$ H&amp;amp;K
lines if the local temperature is ensuremath≥5000 K. The whole atmosphere may
couple to a global, large-scale magnetic field, and lightning may occur on the
nightside.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Understanding the atmospheric properties and chemical composition of the ultra-hot Jupiter HAT-P-7b. II. Mapping the effects of gas kinetics</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publications/2020-aa-635-a-31-m.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publications/2020-aa-635-a-31-m.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Aims: The atmospheres of ultra-hot Jupiters (UHJs) are commonly considered
to be at thermochemical equilibrium. We aim to provide disequilibrium chemistry
maps for a global understanding of the chemistry in the atmosphere of HAT-P-7b and
assess the importance of disequilibrium chemistry on UHJs.  Methods: We applied
a hierarchical modeling approach using 97 1D atmospheric profiles from a 3D general
circulation model of HAT-P-7b. For each atmospheric 1D profile, we evaluated our
kinetic cloud formation model consistently with the local gas-phase composition
in chemical equilibrium. This served as input to study the quenching of dominating
CHNO- binding molecules. We evaluated quenching results from a zeroth- order approximation
in comparison to a kinetic gas-phase approach.  Results: We find that the zeroth-order
approach of estimating quenching points agrees well with the full gas-kinetic modeling
results. However, it underestimates the quenching levels by about one order of magnitude
at high temperatures. Chemical disequilibrium has the greatest effect on the nightside
and morning abundance of species such as H, H$_2$O, CH$_4$, CO$_2$, HCN, and all
C$_n$H$_m$ molecules; heavier C$_n$H$_m$ molecules are more affected by disequilibrium
processes. The CO abundance, however, is affected only marginally. While dayside
abundances also notably change, those around the evening terminator of HAT-P-7b
are the least affected by disequilibrium processes. The latter finding may partially
explain the consistency of observed transmission spectra of UHJs with atmospheres
in thermochemical equilibrium. Photochemistry only negligibly affects molecular
abundances and quenching levels.  Conclusions: In general, the quenching points
of the atmosphere of HAT-P-7b are at much lower pressures than in the cooler hot-jupiters.
We propose several avenues to determining the effect of disequilibrium processes
on UHJs that are in general based on abundance and opacity measurements at different
local times. It remains a challenge to completely disentangle this from the chemical
effects of clouds and that of a primordial nonsolar abundance.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Understanding the atmospheric properties and chemical composition of the ultra-hot Jupiter HAT-P-7b. I. Cloud and chemistry mapping</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publications/2019-aa-631-a-79-h.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publications/2019-aa-631-a-79-h.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Context. Of the presently known ensuremath≈3900 exoplanets, sparse spectral
observations are available for ensuremath≈100. Ultra-hot Jupiters have recently
attracted interest from observers and theoreticians alike, as they provide observationally
accessible test cases. Confronting detailed theoretical models with observations
is of preeminent importance in preparation for upcoming space-based telescopes.  Aims:
We aim to study cloud formation on the ultra-hot Jupiter HAT-P-7b, the resulting
composition of the local gas phase, and how their global changes affect wavelength-
dependent observations utilised to derive fundamental properties of the planet.  Methods:
We apply a hierarchical modelling approach as a virtual laboratory to study cloud
formation and gas-phase chemistry. We utilise 97 vertical 1D profiles of a 3D GCM
for HAT-P-7b to evaluate our kinetic cloud formation model consistently with the
local equilibrium gas- phase composition. We use maps and slice views to provide
a global understanding of the cloud and gas chemistry.  Results: The day/night temperature
difference on HAT-P-7b (ensuremathΔT ensuremath≈ 2500 K) causes clouds to form on
the nightside (dominated by H$_2$/He) while the dayside (dominated by H/He) retains
cloud-free equatorial regions. The cloud particles vary in composition and size
throughout the vertical extension of the cloud, but also globally. TiO$_2$[s]/Al$_2$O$_3$[s]/CaTiO$_3$[s]-particles
of cm- sized radii occur in the higher dayside-latitudes, resulting in a dayside
dominated by gas-phase opacity. The opacity on the nightside, however, is dominated
by 0.01textellipsis0.1ensuremathμm particles made of a material mix dominated by
silicates. The gas pressure at which the atmosphere becomes optically thick is 10$^-4$
bar in cloudy regions, and 0.1 bar in cloud-free regions.  Conclusions: HAT-P-7b
features strong morning/evening terminator asymmetries, providing an example of
patchy clouds and azimuthally-inhomogeneous chemistry. Variable terminator properties
may be accessible by ingress/egress transmission photometry (e.g., CHEOPS and PLATO)
or spectroscopy. The large temperature differences of ensuremath≈2500 K result in
an increasing geometrical extension from the night- to the dayside. The H$_2$O abundance
at the terminator changes by &amp;lt;1 dex with altitude and ensuremathłesssim0.3 dex (a
factor of 2) across the terminator for a given pressure, indicating that H$_2$O
abundances derived from transmission spectra can be representative of the well-mixed
metallicity at P ensuremathgtrsim 10 bar. We suggest the atmospheric C/O as an important
tool to trace the presence and location of clouds in exoplanet atmospheres. The
atmospheric C/O can be sub- and supersolar due to cloud formation. Phase curve variability
of HAT-P-7b is unlikely to be caused by dayside clouds.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Need for Laboratory Measurements and Ab Initio Studies to Aid Understanding of Exoplanetary Atmospheres</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publications/2019-astro-2020-t-146-f.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publications/2019-astro-2020-t-146-f.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We are now in the new era of the characterization of exoplanet atmospheres.
However, atmosphere models are often limited by insufficiencies in the laboratory
and theoretical data that serve as critical inputs. Here we provide descriptions
of areas where new investigations could fill critical gaps in our ability to model
exoplanet atmospheres.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A chemical survey of exoplanets with ARIEL</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publications/2018-ex-a-46-135-t.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Nov 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publications/2018-ex-a-46-135-t.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Thousands of exoplanets have now been discovered with a huge range of masses,
sizes and orbits: from rocky Earth-like planets to large gas giants grazing the
surface of their host star. However, the essential nature of these exoplanets
remains largely mysterious: there is no known, discernible pattern linking the
presence, size, or orbital parameters of a planet to the nature of its parent
star. We have little idea whether the chemistry of a planet is linked to its formation
environment, or whether the type of host star drives the physics and chemistry
of the planet&amp;rsquo;s birth, and evolution. ARIEL was conceived to observe a large number
( 1000) of transiting planets for statistical understanding, including gas giants,
Neptunes, super-Earths and Earth-size planets around a range of host star types
using transit spectroscopy in the 1.25-7.8 ensuremathμm spectral range and multiple
narrow-band photometry in the optical. ARIEL will focus on warm and hot planets
to take advantage of their well-mixed atmospheres which should show minimal condensation
and sequestration of high-Z materials compared to their colder Solar System siblings.
Said warm and hot atmospheres are expected to be more representative of the planetary
bulk composition. Observations of these warm/hot exoplanets, and in particular
of their elemental composition (especially C, O, N, S, Si), will allow the understanding
of the early stages of planetary and atmospheric formation during the nebular
phase and the following few million years. ARIEL will thus provide a representative
picture of the chemical nature of the exoplanets and relate this directly to the
type and chemical environment of the host star. ARIEL is designed as a dedicated
survey mission for combined-light spectroscopy, capable of observing a large and
well-defined planet sample within its 4-year mission lifetime. Transit, eclipse
and phase-curve spectroscopy methods, whereby the signal from the star and planet
are differentiated using knowledge of the planetary ephemerides, allow us to measure
atmospheric signals from the planet at levels of 10-100 part per million (ppm)
relative to the star and, given the bright nature of targets, also allows more
sophisticated techniques, such as eclipse mapping, to give a deeper insight into
the nature of the atmosphere. These types of observations require a stable payload
and satellite platform with broad, instantaneous wavelength coverage to detect
many molecular species, probe the thermal structure, identify clouds and monitor
the stellar activity. The wavelength range proposed covers all the expected major
atmospheric gases from e.g. H$_2$O, CO$_2$, CH$_4$ NH$_3$, HCN, H$_2$S through
to the more exotic metallic compounds, such as TiO, VO, and condensed species.
Simulations of ARIEL performance in conducting exoplanet surveys have been performed&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;using conservative estimates of mission performance and a full model of all
significant noise sources in the measurement&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;using a list of potential ARIEL targets that incorporates the latest available exoplanet statistics.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The conclusion
at the end of the Phase A study, is that ARIEL - in line with the stated mission
objectives - will be able to observe about 1000 exoplanets depending on the details
of the adopted survey strategy, thus confirming the feasibility of the main science
objectives.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Transiting Exoplanet Community Early Release Science Program for JWST</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publications/2018-pasp-130-k-4402-b.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Nov 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publications/2018-pasp-130-k-4402-b.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Add the &lt;strong&gt;full text&lt;/strong&gt; or &lt;strong&gt;supplementary notes&lt;/strong&gt; for the publication here using Markdown formatting.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The GTC exoplanet transit spectroscopy survey. VIII. Flat transmission spectrum for the warm gas giant WASP-80b</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publications/2018-aa-609-a-33-p.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publications/2018-aa-609-a-33-p.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Add the &lt;strong&gt;full text&lt;/strong&gt; or &lt;strong&gt;supplementary notes&lt;/strong&gt; for the publication here using Markdown formatting.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The GTC exoplanet transit spectroscopy survey . VII. An optical transmission spectrum of WASP-48b</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publications/2017-aa-605-a-114-m.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publications/2017-aa-605-a-114-m.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Add the &lt;strong&gt;full text&lt;/strong&gt; or &lt;strong&gt;supplementary notes&lt;/strong&gt; for the publication here using Markdown formatting.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Exploring Other Worlds: Science Questions for Future Direct Imaging Missions (EXOPAG SAG15 Report)</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publications/2017-ar-xiv-170802821-a.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publications/2017-ar-xiv-170802821-a.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Add the &lt;strong&gt;full text&lt;/strong&gt; or &lt;strong&gt;supplementary notes&lt;/strong&gt; for the publication here using Markdown formatting.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The GTC exoplanet transit spectroscopy survey. IV. Confirmation of the flat transmission spectrum of HAT-P-32b</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publications/2016-aa-594-a-65-n.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publications/2016-aa-594-a-65-n.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Add the &lt;strong&gt;full text&lt;/strong&gt; or &lt;strong&gt;supplementary notes&lt;/strong&gt; for the publication here using Markdown formatting.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The GTC exoplanet transit spectroscopy survey. III. No asymmetries in the transit of CoRoT-29b</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publications/2016-aa-589-a-62-p.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 May 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publications/2016-aa-589-a-62-p.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Add the &lt;strong&gt;full text&lt;/strong&gt; or &lt;strong&gt;supplementary notes&lt;/strong&gt; for the publication here using Markdown formatting.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The GTC exoplanet transit spectroscopy survey. II. An overly large Rayleigh-like feature for exoplanet TrES-3b</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publications/2016-aa-585-a-114-p.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publications/2016-aa-585-a-114-p.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Add the &lt;strong&gt;full text&lt;/strong&gt; or &lt;strong&gt;supplementary notes&lt;/strong&gt; for the publication here using Markdown formatting.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The EChO science case</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publications/2015-ex-a-40-329-t.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Dec 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publications/2015-ex-a-40-329-t.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Add the &lt;strong&gt;full text&lt;/strong&gt; or &lt;strong&gt;supplementary notes&lt;/strong&gt; for the publication here using Markdown formatting.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Further Constraints on the Optical Transmission Spectrum of HAT-P-1b</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publications/2015-ap-j-811-55-m.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Sep 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publications/2015-ap-j-811-55-m.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Add the &lt;strong&gt;full text&lt;/strong&gt; or &lt;strong&gt;supplementary notes&lt;/strong&gt; for the publication here using Markdown formatting.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Characterizing Transiting Planet Atmospheres through 2025</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publications/2015-pasp-127-311-c.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Mar 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publications/2015-pasp-127-311-c.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Add the &lt;strong&gt;full text&lt;/strong&gt; or &lt;strong&gt;supplementary notes&lt;/strong&gt; for the publication here using Markdown formatting.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The atmospheric chemistry of the warm Neptune GJ 3470b: Influence of metallicity and temperature on the CH$_4$/CO ratio</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publications/2014-aa-562-a-51-v.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Feb 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publications/2014-aa-562-a-51-v.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Add the &lt;strong&gt;full text&lt;/strong&gt; or &lt;strong&gt;supplementary notes&lt;/strong&gt; for the publication here using Markdown formatting.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Puzzling Chemical Composition of GJ 436b&#39;s Atmosphere: Influence of Tidal Heating on the Chemistry</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publications/2014-ap-j-781-68-a.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Feb 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publications/2014-ap-j-781-68-a.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Add the &lt;strong&gt;full text&lt;/strong&gt; or &lt;strong&gt;supplementary notes&lt;/strong&gt; for the publication here using Markdown formatting.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>On the heat redistribution of the hot transiting exoplanet WASP-18b</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publications/2013-icar-226-1719-i.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Nov 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publications/2013-icar-226-1719-i.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Add the &lt;strong&gt;full text&lt;/strong&gt; or &lt;strong&gt;supplementary notes&lt;/strong&gt; for the publication here using Markdown formatting.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Habitability and Multistability in Earth-like Planets</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publications/2013-an-334-576-l.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jun 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publications/2013-an-334-576-l.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Add the &lt;strong&gt;full text&lt;/strong&gt; or &lt;strong&gt;supplementary notes&lt;/strong&gt; for the publication here using Markdown formatting.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Spitzer 3.6 and 4.5 ensuremathμm full-orbit light curves of WASP-18</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publications/2013-mnras-428-2645-m.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publications/2013-mnras-428-2645-m.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Add the &lt;strong&gt;full text&lt;/strong&gt; or &lt;strong&gt;supplementary notes&lt;/strong&gt; for the publication here using Markdown formatting.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The impact of atmospheric circulation on the chemistry of the hot Jupiter HD 209458b</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publications/2012-aa-548-a-73-a.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Dec 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publications/2012-aa-548-a-73-a.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Add the &lt;strong&gt;full text&lt;/strong&gt; or &lt;strong&gt;supplementary notes&lt;/strong&gt; for the publication here using Markdown formatting.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A chemical model for the atmosphere of hot Jupiters</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publications/2012-aa-546-a-43-v.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Oct 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publications/2012-aa-546-a-43-v.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Add the &lt;strong&gt;full text&lt;/strong&gt; or &lt;strong&gt;supplementary notes&lt;/strong&gt; for the publication here using Markdown formatting.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Transmission spectroscopy of the sodium &#39;D&#39; doublet in WASP-17b with the VLT</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publications/2011-mnras-412-2376-w.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Apr 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publications/2011-mnras-412-2376-w.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Add the &lt;strong&gt;full text&lt;/strong&gt; or &lt;strong&gt;supplementary notes&lt;/strong&gt; for the publication here using Markdown formatting.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>On the Volatile Enrichments and Heavy Element Content in HD189733b</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publications/2011-ap-j-727-77-m.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Feb 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publications/2011-ap-j-727-77-m.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Add the &lt;strong&gt;full text&lt;/strong&gt; or &lt;strong&gt;supplementary notes&lt;/strong&gt; for the publication here using Markdown formatting.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Time-Dependent Radiative Model for the Atmosphere of the Eccentric Exoplanets</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publications/2010-ap-j-712-218-i.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Mar 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publications/2010-ap-j-712-218-i.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Add the &lt;strong&gt;full text&lt;/strong&gt; or &lt;strong&gt;supplementary notes&lt;/strong&gt; for the publication here using Markdown formatting.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A correlation between the heavy element content of transiting extrasolar planets and the metallicity of their parent stars</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publications/2006-aa-453-l-21-g.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jul 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publications/2006-aa-453-l-21-g.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Add the &lt;strong&gt;full text&lt;/strong&gt; or &lt;strong&gt;supplementary notes&lt;/strong&gt; for the publication here using Markdown formatting.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A time-dependent radiative model of HD 209458b</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publications/2005-aa-436-719-i.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jun 2005 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publications/2005-aa-436-719-i.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Add the &lt;strong&gt;full text&lt;/strong&gt; or &lt;strong&gt;supplementary notes&lt;/strong&gt; for the publication here using Markdown formatting.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Nonradial and nonpolytropic astrophysical outflows. VII. Fitting ULYSSES solar wind data during minimum</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publications/2005-aa-432-687-s.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Mar 2005 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publications/2005-aa-432-687-s.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Add the &lt;strong&gt;full text&lt;/strong&gt; or &lt;strong&gt;supplementary notes&lt;/strong&gt; for the publication here using Markdown formatting.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>An interpretation of the nitrogen deficiency in comets</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publications/2003-icar-161-511-i.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Feb 2003 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publications/2003-icar-161-511-i.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Add the &lt;strong&gt;full text&lt;/strong&gt; or &lt;strong&gt;supplementary notes&lt;/strong&gt; for the publication here using Markdown formatting.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/admin.yml</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/admin.yml</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
