<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Astrophysics - Solar and Stellar Astrophysics | Nicolas Iro</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/tag/astrophysics-solar-and-stellar-astrophysics.html</link>
      <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/tag/astrophysics-solar-and-stellar-astrophysics/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Astrophysics - Solar and Stellar Astrophysics</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 01 Jun 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>http://localhost:1313/media/logo_hu_a8d074ae3d848875.png</url>
      <title>Astrophysics - Solar and Stellar Astrophysics</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/tag/astrophysics-solar-and-stellar-astrophysics.html</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>The PLATO mission</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publications/2025-ex-a-59-26-r.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jun 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publications/2025-ex-a-59-26-r.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;PLATO (PLAnetary Transits and Oscillations of stars) is ESA&amp;rsquo;s M3 mission
designed to detect and characterise extrasolar planets and perform asteroseismic
monitoring of a large number of stars. PLATO will detect small planets (down to
&amp;lt;2REarth) around bright stars (&amp;lt;11 mag), including terrestrial planets in the habitable
zone of solar-like stars. With the complement of radial velocity observations from
the ground, planets will be characterised for their radius, mass, and age with high
accuracy (5%, 10%, 10% for an Earth-Sun combination respectively). PLATO will provide
us with a large-scale catalogue of well-characterised small planets up to intermediate
orbital periods, relevant for a meaningful comparison to planet formation theories
and to better understand planet evolution. It will make possible comparative exoplanetology
to place our Solar System planets in a broader context. In parallel, PLATO will
study (host) stars using asteroseismology, allowing us to determine the stellar
properties with high accuracy, substantially enhancing our knowledge of stellar
structure and evolution. The payload instrument consists of 26 cameras with 12cm
aperture each. For at least four years, the mission will perform high-precision
photometric measurements. Here we review the science objectives, present PLATO&amp;rsquo;s
target samples and fields, provide an overview of expected core science performance
as well as a description of the instrument and the mission profile towards the end
of the serial production of the flight cameras. PLATO is scheduled for a launch
date end 2026. This overview therefore provides a summary of the mission to the
community in preparation of the upcoming operational phases.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A roadmap for the atmospheric characterization of terrestrial exoplanets with JWST</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publications/2024-nat-as-8-810-t.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publications/2024-nat-as-8-810-t.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Ultracool dwarf stars are abundant, long-lived and uniquely suited to enable
the atmospheric study of transiting terrestrial companions with the JWST. Among
them, the most prominent is the M8.5V star TRAPPIST-1 and its seven planets. While
JWST Cycle 1 observations have started to yield preliminary insights into the planets,
they have also revealed that their atmospheric exploration requires a better understanding
of their host star. Here we propose a roadmap to characterize the TRAPPIST-1 system
— and others like it — in an efficient and robust manner with JWST. We notably recommend
that — although more challenging to schedule — multi-transit windows be prioritized
to mitigate the effects of stellar activity and gather up to twice more transits
per JWST hour spent. We conclude that, for such systems, planets cannot be studied
in isolation by small programmes but rather need large-scale, joint space- and ground-
based initiatives to fully exploit the capabilities of JWST for the exploration
of terrestrial planets.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Impact of Cosmic Rays on Atmospheric Ion Chemistry and Spectral Transmission Features of TRAPPIST-1e</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publications/2024-ap-j-961-164-h.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Feb 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publications/2024-ap-j-961-164-h.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Ongoing observing projects like the James Webb Space Telescope and future
missions offer the chance to characterize Earth-like exoplanetary atmospheres. Thereby,
M dwarfs are preferred targets for transit observations, for example, due to their
favorable planet–star contrast ratio. However, the radiation and particle environment
of these cool stars could be far more extreme than what we know from the Sun. Thus,
knowing the stellar radiation and particle environment and its possible influence
on detectable biosignatures—in particular, signs of life like ozone and methane—is
crucial to understanding upcoming transit spectra. In this study, with the help
of our unique model suite INCREASE, we investigate the impact of a strong stellar
energetic particle event on the atmospheric ionization, neutral and ion chemistry,
and atmospheric biosignatures of TRAPPIST-1e. Therefore, transit spectra for six
scenarios are simulated. We find that a Carrington-like event drastically increases
atmospheric ionization and induces substantial changes in ion chemistry and spectral
transmission features: all scenarios show high event- induced amounts of nitrogen
dioxide (i.e., at 6.2 ensuremathμm), a reduction of the atmospheric transit depth
in all water bands (i.e., at 5.5–7.0 ensuremathμm), a decrease of the methane bands
(i.e., at 3.0–3.5 ensuremathμm), and depletion of ozone (i.e., at ensuremath∼9.6
ensuremathμm). Therefore, it is essential to include high-energy particle effects
to correctly assign biosignature signals from, e.g., ozone and methane. We further
show that the nitric acid feature at 11.0–12.0 ensuremathμm, discussed as a proxy
for stellar particle contamination, is absent in wet-dead atmospheres.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Early Release Science of the exoplanet WASP-39b with JWST NIRCam</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publications/2023-natur-614-653-a.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publications/2023-natur-614-653-a.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Measuring the metallicity and carbon-to-oxygen (C/O) ratio in exoplanet
atmospheres is a fundamental step towards constraining the dominant chemical processes
at work and, if in equilibrium, revealing planet formation histories. Transmission
spectroscopy (for example, refs. $^1,2$) provides the necessary means by constraining
the abundances of oxygen- and carbon-bearing species; however, this requires broad
wavelength coverage, moderate spectral resolution and high precision, which, together,
are not achievable with previous observatories. Now that JWST has commenced science
operations, we are able to observe exoplanets at previously uncharted wavelengths
and spectral resolutions. Here we report time-series observations of the transiting
exoplanet WASP-39b using JWST&amp;rsquo;s Near InfraRed Camera (NIRCam). The long-wavelength
spectroscopic and short- wavelength photometric light curves span 2.0-4.0 micrometres,
exhibit minimal systematics and reveal well defined molecular absorption features
in the planet&amp;rsquo;s spectrum. Specifically, we detect gaseous water in the atmosphere
and place an upper limit on the abundance of methane. The otherwise prominent carbon
dioxide feature at 2.8 micrometres is largely masked by water. The best-fit chemical
equilibrium models favour an atmospheric metallicity of 1-100-times solar (that
is, an enrichment of elements heavier than helium relative to the Sun) and a substellar
C/O ratio. The inferred high metallicity and low C/O ratio may indicate significant
accretion of solid materials during planet formation (for example, refs. $^3,4$$^,$)
or disequilibrium processes in the upper atmosphere (for example, refs. $^5,6$).&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Early Release Science of the exoplanet WASP-39b with JWST NIRISS</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publications/2023-natur-614-670-f.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publications/2023-natur-614-670-f.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The Saturn-mass exoplanet WASP-39b has been the subject of extensive efforts
to determine its atmospheric properties using transmission spectroscopy$^1-4$. However,
these efforts have been hampered by modelling degeneracies between composition and
cloud properties that are caused by limited data quality$^5-9$. Here we present
the transmission spectrum of WASP-39b obtained using the Single-Object Slitless
Spectroscopy (SOSS) mode of the Near Infrared Imager and Slitless Spectrograph (NIRISS)
instrument on the JWST. This spectrum spans 0.6-2.8 ensuremathμm in wavelength and
shows several water-absorption bands, the potassium resonance doublet and signatures
of clouds. The precision and broad wavelength coverage of NIRISS/SOSS allows us
to break model degeneracies between cloud properties and the atmospheric composition
of WASP-39b, favouring a heavy-element enhancement (`metallicity&amp;rsquo;) of about 10-30
times the solar value, a sub-solar carbon-to- oxygen (C/O) ratio and a solar-to-super-solar
potassium-to- oxygen (K/O) ratio. The observations are also best explained by wavelength-dependent,
non-grey clouds with inhomogeneous coverageof the planet&amp;rsquo;s terminator.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Early Release Science of the exoplanet WASP-39b with JWST NIRSpec G395H</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publications/2023-natur-614-664-a.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publications/2023-natur-614-664-a.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Measuring the abundances of carbon and oxygen in exoplanet atmospheres is
considered a crucial avenue for unlocking the formation and evolution of exoplanetary
systems$^1,2$. Access to the chemical inventory of an exoplanet requires high-precision
observations, often inferred from individual molecular detections with low-resolution
space-based$^3-5$ and high- resolution ground-based$^6-8$ facilities. Here we report
the medium-resolution (R ensuremath≈ 600) transmission spectrum of an exoplanet
atmosphere between 3 and 5 ensuremathμm covering several absorption features for
the Saturn-mass exoplanet WASP-39b (ref. $^9$), obtained with the Near Infrared
Spectrograph (NIRSpec) G395H grating of JWST. Our observations achieve 1.46 times
photon precision, providing an average transit depth uncertainty of 221 ppm per
spectroscopic bin, and present minimal impacts from systematic effects. We detect
significant absorption from CO$_2$ (28.5ensuremathσ) and H$_2$O (21.5ensuremathσ),
and identify SO$_2$ as the source of absorption at 4.1 ensuremathμm (4.8ensuremathσ).
Best-fit atmospheric models range between 3 and 10 times solar metallicity, with
sub-solar to solar C/O ratios. These results, including the detection of SO$_2$,
underscore the importance of characterizing the chemistry in exoplanet atmospheres
and showcase NIRSpec G395H as an excellent mode for time-series observations over
this critical wavelength range$^10$.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Early Release Science of the exoplanet WASP-39b with JWST NIRSpec PRISM</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publications/2023-natur-614-659-r.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publications/2023-natur-614-659-r.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Transmission spectroscopy$^1-3$ of exoplanets has revealed signatures of
water vapour, aerosols and alkali metals in a few dozen exoplanet atmospheres$^4,5$.
However, these previous inferences with the Hubble and Spitzer Space Telescopes
were hindered by the observations&amp;rsquo; relatively narrow wavelength range and spectral
resolving power, which precluded the unambiguous identification of other chemical
species—in particular the primary carbon-bearing molecules$^6,7$. Here we report
a broad-wavelength 0.5-5.5 textmum atmospheric transmission spectrum of WASP-39b$^8$,
a 1,200 K, roughly Saturn-mass, Jupiter-radius exoplanet, measured with the JWST
NIRSpec&amp;rsquo;s PRISM mode$^9$ as part of the JWST Transiting Exoplanet Community Early
Release Science Team Program$^10-12$. We robustly detect several chemical species
at high significance, including Na (19σ), H$_2$O (33σ), CO$_2$
(28σ) and CO (7σ). The non-detection of CH$_4$, combined with
a strong CO$_2$ feature, favours atmospheric models with a super-solar atmospheric
metallicity. An unanticipated absorption feature at 4 textmum is best explained
by SO$_2$ (2.7σ), which could be a tracer of atmospheric photochemistry.
These observations demonstrate JWST&amp;rsquo;s sensitivity to a rich diversity of exoplanet
compositions and chemical processes.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Understanding the atmospheric properties and chemical composition of the ultra-hot Jupiter HAT-P-7b. III. Changing ionisation and the emergence of an ionosphere</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publications/2021-aa-648-a-80-h.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publications/2021-aa-648-a-80-h.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Context. Ultra-hot Jupiters are the hottest exoplanets that have been discovered
so far. They present a unique possibility to explore hot and cold chemistry on
one object. The tidally locked ultra- hot Jupiter HAT-P-7b has a day-to-night
temperature difference of ≃2500 K, confining cloud formation to the nightside
and efficient ionisation to the dayside. Both have distinct observational signatures.
Aims: We analyse plasma and magnetic processes in the atmosphere of the ultra-hot
Jupiter HAT-P-7b to investigate the formation of an ionosphere and the possibility
of magnetically coupling the atmospheric gas as the base for an extended exosphere.
We show which ions and atoms may be used as spectral tracers, and if and where
conditions for lightning may occur within the clouds of HAT-P-7b.  Methods: We
used 3D modelling results as input for a kinetic cloud formation code and evaluated
characteristic plasma and magnetic coupling parameters. A local thermodynamical
equilibrium radiative transfer was solved for the ionised gas phase. This study&lt;br&gt;
is confined to thermal ionisation only.  Results: The ionisation throughout HAT-P-7b&amp;rsquo;s
atmosphere varies drastically between day- and nightside. The dayside has high
levels of thermal ionisation and long-range electromagnetic interactions dominate
over kinetic electron-neutral interactions, suggesting a day-night difference
in magnetic coupling. K$^+$, Na$^+$, Li$^+$, Ca$^+$, and Al$^+$ are more abundant
than their atomic counterparts on the dayside. The minimum magnetic flux density
for electrons for magnetic coupling is B &amp;lt; 0.5 G for all regions of HAT-P-7b&amp;rsquo;s
atmosphere.  Conclusions: HAT-P-7b&amp;rsquo;s dayside has an asymmetric ionosphere that
extends deep into the atmosphere, the nightside has no thermally driven ionosphere.
A corresponding asymmetry is imprinted in the ion and neutral composition at the
terminators. The ionosphere on HAT-P-7b may be directly traced by the Ca$^+$ H&amp;amp;K
lines if the local temperature is ensuremath≥5000 K. The whole atmosphere may
couple to a global, large-scale magnetic field, and lightning may occur on the
nightside.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Understanding the atmospheric properties and chemical composition of the ultra-hot Jupiter HAT-P-7b. I. Cloud and chemistry mapping</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publications/2019-aa-631-a-79-h.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publications/2019-aa-631-a-79-h.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Context. Of the presently known ensuremath≈3900 exoplanets, sparse spectral
observations are available for ensuremath≈100. Ultra-hot Jupiters have recently
attracted interest from observers and theoreticians alike, as they provide observationally
accessible test cases. Confronting detailed theoretical models with observations
is of preeminent importance in preparation for upcoming space-based telescopes.  Aims:
We aim to study cloud formation on the ultra-hot Jupiter HAT-P-7b, the resulting
composition of the local gas phase, and how their global changes affect wavelength-
dependent observations utilised to derive fundamental properties of the planet.  Methods:
We apply a hierarchical modelling approach as a virtual laboratory to study cloud
formation and gas-phase chemistry. We utilise 97 vertical 1D profiles of a 3D GCM
for HAT-P-7b to evaluate our kinetic cloud formation model consistently with the
local equilibrium gas- phase composition. We use maps and slice views to provide
a global understanding of the cloud and gas chemistry.  Results: The day/night temperature
difference on HAT-P-7b (ensuremathΔT ensuremath≈ 2500 K) causes clouds to form on
the nightside (dominated by H$_2$/He) while the dayside (dominated by H/He) retains
cloud-free equatorial regions. The cloud particles vary in composition and size
throughout the vertical extension of the cloud, but also globally. TiO$_2$[s]/Al$_2$O$_3$[s]/CaTiO$_3$[s]-particles
of cm- sized radii occur in the higher dayside-latitudes, resulting in a dayside
dominated by gas-phase opacity. The opacity on the nightside, however, is dominated
by 0.01textellipsis0.1ensuremathμm particles made of a material mix dominated by
silicates. The gas pressure at which the atmosphere becomes optically thick is 10$^-4$
bar in cloudy regions, and 0.1 bar in cloud-free regions.  Conclusions: HAT-P-7b
features strong morning/evening terminator asymmetries, providing an example of
patchy clouds and azimuthally-inhomogeneous chemistry. Variable terminator properties
may be accessible by ingress/egress transmission photometry (e.g., CHEOPS and PLATO)
or spectroscopy. The large temperature differences of ensuremath≈2500 K result in
an increasing geometrical extension from the night- to the dayside. The H$_2$O abundance
at the terminator changes by &amp;lt;1 dex with altitude and ensuremathłesssim0.3 dex (a
factor of 2) across the terminator for a given pressure, indicating that H$_2$O
abundances derived from transmission spectra can be representative of the well-mixed
metallicity at P ensuremathgtrsim 10 bar. We suggest the atmospheric C/O as an important
tool to trace the presence and location of clouds in exoplanet atmospheres. The
atmospheric C/O can be sub- and supersolar due to cloud formation. Phase curve variability
of HAT-P-7b is unlikely to be caused by dayside clouds.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Transmission spectroscopy of the sodium &#39;D&#39; doublet in WASP-17b with the VLT</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publications/2011-mnras-412-2376-w.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Apr 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publications/2011-mnras-412-2376-w.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Add the &lt;strong&gt;full text&lt;/strong&gt; or &lt;strong&gt;supplementary notes&lt;/strong&gt; for the publication here using Markdown formatting.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
