<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Earth and Planetary Astrophysics | Nicolas Iro</title><link>https://ironick.github.io/tag/earth-and-planetary-astrophysics.html</link><atom:link href="https://ironick.github.io/tag/earth-and-planetary-astrophysics/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><description>Earth and Planetary Astrophysics</description><generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><image><url>https://ironick.github.io/media/logo_hu3811882414585691295.png</url><title>Earth and Planetary Astrophysics</title><link>https://ironick.github.io/tag/earth-and-planetary-astrophysics.html</link></image><item><title>Horizontal and vertical exoplanet thermal structure from a JWST spectroscopic eclipse map</title><link>https://ironick.github.io/publications/2025-ar-xiv-251024708-c.html</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ironick.github.io/publications/2025-ar-xiv-251024708-c.html</guid><description>&lt;p>Highly-irradiated giant exoplanets known as &amp;lsquo;&amp;lsquo;ultra-hot Jupiters&amp;rsquo;&amp;rsquo; are
anticipated to exhibit large variations of atmospheric temperature and chemistry
as a function of longitude, latitude, and altitude. Previous observations have
hinted at these variations, but the existing data have been fundamentally restricted
to probing hemisphere-integrated spectra, thereby providing only coarse information
on atmospheric gradients. Here we present a spectroscopic eclipse map of an extrasolar
planet, resolving the atmosphere in multiple dimensions simultaneously. We analyze
a secondary eclipse of the ultra-hot Jupiter WASP-18b observed with the NIRISS
instrument on JWST. The mapping reveals weaker longitudinal temperature gradients
than were predicted by theoretical models, indicating the importance of hydrogen
dissociation and/or nightside clouds in shaping global thermal emission. Additionally,
we identify two thermally distinct regions of the planet&amp;rsquo;s atmosphere: a &amp;lsquo;&amp;lsquo;hotspot&amp;rsquo;&amp;rsquo;
surrounding the substellar point and a &amp;ldquo;ring&amp;rdquo; near the dayside limbs. The hotspot
region shows a strongly inverted thermal structure due to the presence of optical
absorbers and a water abundance marginally lower than the hemispheric average,
in accordance with theoretical predictions. The ring region shows colder temperatures
and poorly constrained chemical abundances. Similar future analyses will reveal
three-dimensional thermal, chemical, and dynamical properties of a broad range
of exoplanet atmospheres.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>First JWST thermal phase curves of temperate terrestrial exoplanets reveal no thick atmosphere around TRAPPIST-1 b and c</title><link>https://ironick.github.io/publications/2025-ar-xiv-250902128-g.html</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Sep 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ironick.github.io/publications/2025-ar-xiv-250902128-g.html</guid><description>&lt;p>We report JWST/MIRI 15 μm phase curves of TRAPPIST-1 b and c, revealing
thermal emission consistent with their irradiation levels, assuming no efficient
heat redistribution. We find that TRAPPIST-1 b shows a high dayside brightness temperature
(490 ± 17 K), no significantly detectable nightside emission (F[b, Night,
max] = 39_-27^+55 ppm), and no phase offset &amp;ndash; features consistent with a low-albedo,
airless ultramafic rocky surface. TRAPPIST-1 c exhibits a lower dayside brightness
temperature (369 ± 23 K), and a nightside flux statistically indistinguishable
from that of TRAPPIST-1 b (F[c, Night, max] = 62_-43^+60 ppm). Atmosphere models
with surface pressures $≥$1 bar and efficient greenhouse effects are strongly disfavoured
for both planets. TRAPPIST-1 b is unlikely to possess any substantial atmosphere,
while TRAPPIST-1 c may retain a tenuous, greenhouse-poor O$_2$-dominated atmosphere
or be similarly airless with a more reflective surface. These results suggest divergent
evolutionary pathways or atmospheric loss processes, despite similar compositions.
These measurements tightly constrain atmosphere retention in the inner TRAPPIST-1
system.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Limb Asymmetries on WASP-39b: A Multi-GCM Comparison of Chemistry, Clouds, and Hazes</title><link>https://ironick.github.io/publications/2025-ar-xiv-250921588-s.html</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Sep 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ironick.github.io/publications/2025-ar-xiv-250921588-s.html</guid><description>&lt;p>With JWST, observing separate spectra of the morning and evening limbs of
hot Jupiters has finally become a reality. The first such observation was reported
for WASP-39b, where the evening terminator was observed to have a larger transit
radius by about 400 ppm and a stronger 4.3 μm CO2 feature than the morning
terminator. Multiple factors, including temperature differences, photo/thermochemistry,
clouds and hazes, could cause such limb asymmetries. To interpret these new limb
asymmetry observations, a detailed understanding of how the relevant processes affect
morning and evening spectra grounded in forward models is needed. Focusing on WASP-39b,
we compare simulations from five different general circulation models (GCMs), including
one simulating disequilibrium thermochemistry and one with cloud radiative feedback,
to the recent WASP-39b limb asymmetry observations. We also post-process the temperature
structures of all simulations with a 2D photochemical model and one simulation with
a cloud microphysics model. Although the temperatures predicted by the different
models vary considerably, the models are remarkably consistent in their predicted
morning&amp;ndash;evening temperature differences. Several equilibrium-chemistry simulations
predict strong methane features in the morning spectrum, not seen in the observations.
When including disequilibrium processes, horizontal transport homogenizes methane,
and these methane features disappear. However, even after including photochemistry
and clouds, our models still cannot reproduce the observed ∼2000 ppm asymmetry
in the CO2 feature. A combination of factors, such as varying metallicity and
unexplored parameters in cloud models, may explain the discrepancy, emphasizing
the need for future models integrating cloud microphysics and feedback across a
broader parameter space.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Dark skies of the slightly eccentric WASP-18 b from its optical-to-infrared dayside emission</title><link>https://ironick.github.io/publications/2025-aa-699-a-150-d.html</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Jul 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ironick.github.io/publications/2025-aa-699-a-150-d.html</guid><description>&lt;p>Context. Ultra-hot Jupiters (UHJs) are gas giant exoplanets that are strongly
irradiated by their star, setting intense molecular dissociation that leads to atmospheric
chemistry dominated by ions and atoms. These conditions inhibit day-to-night heat
redistribution, which results in high temperature contrasts. Phase-curve observations
over several passbands offer insights on the thermal structure and properties of
these extreme atmospheres. Aims. We aim to perform a joint analysis of multiple
observations of WASP-18 b from the visible to the mid- infrared, using data from
CHEOPS, TESS, and Spitzer. Our purpose is to characterise the planetary atmosphere
with a consistent view over the large wavelength range covered, including JWST data.
Methods. We implemented a model for the planetary signal including transits, occultations,
phase signal, ellipsoidal variations, Doppler boosting, and light travel time. We
performed a joint fit of more than 250 eclipse events and derived the atmospheric
properties using general circulation models (GCMs) and retrieval analyses. Results.
We obtained new ephemerides with unprecedented precisions of 1 second and 1.4 millisecond
on the time of inferior conjunction and orbital period, respectively. We computed
a planetary radius of R $_ p $ = 1.1926 ensuremath± 0.0077 R $_ J $ with a precision
of 0.65% (or 550 km). Based on a timing inconsistency with JWST, we discuss and
confirm the orbital eccentricity (e = 0.00852 ensuremath± 0.00091). We also constrain
the argument of periastron to ensuremathømega = 261.9$_‑1.4$ $^+1.3$ deg. We show
that the large dayside emission implies the presence of magnetic drag and super-solar
metallicity. We find a steep thermally inverted gradient in the planetary atmosphere,
which is common for UHJs. We detected the presence of strong CO emission lines at
4.5 ensuremathμm from an excess of dayside brightness in the Spitzer/IRAC/Channel
2 passband. Using these models to constrain the reflected contribution in the CHEOPS
passband, we derived an extremely low geometric albedo of A$_g$ $^CHEOPS$ = 0.027
ensuremath± 0.011. Conclusions. The orbital eccentricity remains a potential challenge
for planetary dynamics that might require further study given the short-period massive
planet and despite the young age of the system. The characterisation of the atmosphere
of WASP-18 b reveals the necessity to account for magnetic friction and super-solar
metallicity to explain the full picture of the dayside emission. We find the planetary
dayside to be extremely unreflective; however, when juxtaposing TESS and CHEOPS
data, we get hints of increased scattering efficiency in the visible, likely due
to Rayleigh scattering.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>