<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Astrophysics - Instrumentation and Methods for Astrophysics | Nicolas Iro</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/tag/astrophysics-instrumentation-and-methods-for-astrophysics.html</link>
      <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/tag/astrophysics-instrumentation-and-methods-for-astrophysics/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Astrophysics - Instrumentation and Methods for Astrophysics</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 01 Jun 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>http://localhost:1313/media/logo_hu_a8d074ae3d848875.png</url>
      <title>Astrophysics - Instrumentation and Methods for Astrophysics</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/tag/astrophysics-instrumentation-and-methods-for-astrophysics.html</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>The PLATO mission</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publications/2025-ex-a-59-26-r.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jun 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publications/2025-ex-a-59-26-r.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;PLATO (PLAnetary Transits and Oscillations of stars) is ESA&amp;rsquo;s M3 mission
designed to detect and characterise extrasolar planets and perform asteroseismic
monitoring of a large number of stars. PLATO will detect small planets (down to
&amp;lt;2REarth) around bright stars (&amp;lt;11 mag), including terrestrial planets in the habitable
zone of solar-like stars. With the complement of radial velocity observations from
the ground, planets will be characterised for their radius, mass, and age with high
accuracy (5%, 10%, 10% for an Earth-Sun combination respectively). PLATO will provide
us with a large-scale catalogue of well-characterised small planets up to intermediate
orbital periods, relevant for a meaningful comparison to planet formation theories
and to better understand planet evolution. It will make possible comparative exoplanetology
to place our Solar System planets in a broader context. In parallel, PLATO will
study (host) stars using asteroseismology, allowing us to determine the stellar
properties with high accuracy, substantially enhancing our knowledge of stellar
structure and evolution. The payload instrument consists of 26 cameras with 12cm
aperture each. For at least four years, the mission will perform high-precision
photometric measurements. Here we review the science objectives, present PLATO&amp;rsquo;s
target samples and fields, provide an overview of expected core science performance
as well as a description of the instrument and the mission profile towards the end
of the serial production of the flight cameras. PLATO is scheduled for a launch
date end 2026. This overview therefore provides a summary of the mission to the
community in preparation of the upcoming operational phases.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The CUISINES Framework for Conducting Exoplanet Model Intercomparison Projects, Version 1.0</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publications/2024-psj-5-175-s.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publications/2024-psj-5-175-s.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As JWST begins to return observations, it is more important than ever that
exoplanet climate models can consistently and correctly predict the observability
of exoplanets, retrieval of their data, and interpretation of planetary environments
from that data. Model intercomparisons play a crucial role in this context, especially
now when few data are available to validate model predictions. The CUISINES Working
Group of NASA&amp;rsquo;s Nexus for Exoplanet Systems Science supports a systematic approach
to evaluating the performance of exoplanet models and provides here a framework
for conducting community-organized exoplanet model intercomparison projects (exoMIPs).
The CUISINES framework adapts Earth climate community practices specifically for
the needs of the exoplanet researchers, encompassing a range of model types, planetary
targets, and parameter space studies. It is intended to help researchers to work
collectively, equitably, and openly toward common goals. The CUISINES framework
rests on five principles: (1) define in advance what research question(s) the
exoMIP is intended to address, (2) create an experimental design that maximizes
community participation and advertise it widely, (3) plan a project timeline that
allows all exoMIP members to participate fully, (4) generate data products from
model output for direct comparison to observations, and (5) create a data management
plan that is workable in the present and scalable for the future. Within the first
years of its existence, CUISINES is already providing logistical support to 10
exoMIPs and will continue to host annual workshops for further community feedback
and presentation of new exoMIP ideas.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A roadmap for the atmospheric characterization of terrestrial exoplanets with JWST</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publications/2024-nat-as-8-810-t.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publications/2024-nat-as-8-810-t.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Ultracool dwarf stars are abundant, long-lived and uniquely suited to enable
the atmospheric study of transiting terrestrial companions with the JWST. Among
them, the most prominent is the M8.5V star TRAPPIST-1 and its seven planets. While
JWST Cycle 1 observations have started to yield preliminary insights into the planets,
they have also revealed that their atmospheric exploration requires a better understanding
of their host star. Here we propose a roadmap to characterize the TRAPPIST-1 system
— and others like it — in an efficient and robust manner with JWST. We notably recommend
that — although more challenging to schedule — multi-transit windows be prioritized
to mitigate the effects of stellar activity and gather up to twice more transits
per JWST hour spent. We conclude that, for such systems, planets cannot be studied
in isolation by small programmes but rather need large-scale, joint space- and ground-
based initiatives to fully exploit the capabilities of JWST for the exploration
of terrestrial planets.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Nightside clouds and disequilibrium chemistry on the hot Jupiter WASP-43b</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publications/2024-nat-as-8-879-b.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publications/2024-nat-as-8-879-b.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Hot Jupiters are among the best-studied exoplanets, but it is still poorly
understood how their chemical composition and cloud properties vary with longitude.
Theoretical models predict that clouds may condense on the nightside and that molecular
abundances can be driven out of equilibrium by zonal winds. Here we report a phase-resolved
emission spectrum of the hot Jupiter WASP-43b measured from 5 ensuremathμm to 12
ensuremathμm with the JWST&amp;rsquo;s Mid-Infrared Instrument. The spectra reveal a large
day-night temperature contrast (with average brightness temperatures of 1,524 ensuremath±
35 K and 863 ensuremath± 23 K, respectively) and evidence for water absorption at
all orbital phases. Comparisons with three- dimensional atmospheric models show
that both the phase-curve shape and emission spectra strongly suggest the presence
of nightside clouds that become optically thick to thermal emission at pressures
greater than åisebox-0.5ex~100 mbar. The dayside is consistent with a cloudless
atmosphere above the mid-infrared photosphere. Contrary to expectations from equilibrium
chemistry but consistent with disequilibrium kinetics models, methane is not detected
on the nightside (2ensuremathσ upper limit of 1-6 ppm, depending on model assumptions).
Our results provide strong evidence that the atmosphere of WASP-43b is shaped by
disequilibrium processes and provide new insights into the properties of the planet&amp;rsquo;s
nightside clouds. However, the remaining discrepancies between our observations
and our predictive atmospheric models emphasize the importance of further exploring
the effects of clouds and disequilibrium chemistry in numerical models.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A broadband thermal emission spectrum of the ultra-hot Jupiter WASP-18b</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publications/2023-natur-620-292-c.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Aug 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publications/2023-natur-620-292-c.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Close-in giant exoplanets with temperatures greater than 2,000 K (&amp;lsquo;ultra-hot
Jupiters&amp;rsquo;) have been the subject of extensive efforts to determine their atmospheric
properties using thermal emission measurements from the Hubble Space Telescope (HST)
and Spitzer Space Telescope$^1-3$. However, previous studies have yielded inconsistent
results because the small sizes of the spectral features and the limited information
content of the data resulted in high sensitivity to the varying assumptions made
in the treatment of instrument systematics and the atmospheric retrieval analysis$^3-12$.
Here we present a dayside thermal emission spectrum of the ultra-hot Jupiter WASP-18b
obtained with the NIRISS$^13$ instrument on the JWST. The data span 0.85 to 2.85
ensuremathμm in wavelength at an average resolving power of 400 and exhibit minimal
systematics. The spectrum shows three water emission features (at &amp;gt;6σ
confidence) and evidence for optical opacity, possibly attributable to H$^-$,
TiO and VO (combined significance of 3.8σ). Models that fit the data require
a thermal inversion, molecular dissociation as predicted by chemical equilibrium,
a solar heavy-element abundance (&amp;lsquo;metallicity&amp;rsquo;, M/H =1.0 3$_-0.51$$^+1.11$
times solar) and a carbon- to-oxygen (C/O) ratio less than unity. The data also
yield a dayside brightness temperature map, which shows a peak in temperature near
the substellar point that decreases steeply and symmetrically with longitude towards
the terminators.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Early Release Science of the exoplanet WASP-39b with JWST NIRCam</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publications/2023-natur-614-653-a.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publications/2023-natur-614-653-a.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Measuring the metallicity and carbon-to-oxygen (C/O) ratio in exoplanet
atmospheres is a fundamental step towards constraining the dominant chemical processes
at work and, if in equilibrium, revealing planet formation histories. Transmission
spectroscopy (for example, refs. $^1,2$) provides the necessary means by constraining
the abundances of oxygen- and carbon-bearing species; however, this requires broad
wavelength coverage, moderate spectral resolution and high precision, which, together,
are not achievable with previous observatories. Now that JWST has commenced science
operations, we are able to observe exoplanets at previously uncharted wavelengths
and spectral resolutions. Here we report time-series observations of the transiting
exoplanet WASP-39b using JWST&amp;rsquo;s Near InfraRed Camera (NIRCam). The long-wavelength
spectroscopic and short- wavelength photometric light curves span 2.0-4.0 micrometres,
exhibit minimal systematics and reveal well defined molecular absorption features
in the planet&amp;rsquo;s spectrum. Specifically, we detect gaseous water in the atmosphere
and place an upper limit on the abundance of methane. The otherwise prominent carbon
dioxide feature at 2.8 micrometres is largely masked by water. The best-fit chemical
equilibrium models favour an atmospheric metallicity of 1-100-times solar (that
is, an enrichment of elements heavier than helium relative to the Sun) and a substellar
C/O ratio. The inferred high metallicity and low C/O ratio may indicate significant
accretion of solid materials during planet formation (for example, refs. $^3,4$$^,$)
or disequilibrium processes in the upper atmosphere (for example, refs. $^5,6$).&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Early Release Science of the exoplanet WASP-39b with JWST NIRISS</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publications/2023-natur-614-670-f.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publications/2023-natur-614-670-f.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The Saturn-mass exoplanet WASP-39b has been the subject of extensive efforts
to determine its atmospheric properties using transmission spectroscopy$^1-4$. However,
these efforts have been hampered by modelling degeneracies between composition and
cloud properties that are caused by limited data quality$^5-9$. Here we present
the transmission spectrum of WASP-39b obtained using the Single-Object Slitless
Spectroscopy (SOSS) mode of the Near Infrared Imager and Slitless Spectrograph (NIRISS)
instrument on the JWST. This spectrum spans 0.6-2.8 ensuremathμm in wavelength and
shows several water-absorption bands, the potassium resonance doublet and signatures
of clouds. The precision and broad wavelength coverage of NIRISS/SOSS allows us
to break model degeneracies between cloud properties and the atmospheric composition
of WASP-39b, favouring a heavy-element enhancement (`metallicity&amp;rsquo;) of about 10-30
times the solar value, a sub-solar carbon-to- oxygen (C/O) ratio and a solar-to-super-solar
potassium-to- oxygen (K/O) ratio. The observations are also best explained by wavelength-dependent,
non-grey clouds with inhomogeneous coverageof the planet&amp;rsquo;s terminator.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Early Release Science of the exoplanet WASP-39b with JWST NIRSpec G395H</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publications/2023-natur-614-664-a.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publications/2023-natur-614-664-a.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Measuring the abundances of carbon and oxygen in exoplanet atmospheres is
considered a crucial avenue for unlocking the formation and evolution of exoplanetary
systems$^1,2$. Access to the chemical inventory of an exoplanet requires high-precision
observations, often inferred from individual molecular detections with low-resolution
space-based$^3-5$ and high- resolution ground-based$^6-8$ facilities. Here we report
the medium-resolution (R ensuremath≈ 600) transmission spectrum of an exoplanet
atmosphere between 3 and 5 ensuremathμm covering several absorption features for
the Saturn-mass exoplanet WASP-39b (ref. $^9$), obtained with the Near Infrared
Spectrograph (NIRSpec) G395H grating of JWST. Our observations achieve 1.46 times
photon precision, providing an average transit depth uncertainty of 221 ppm per
spectroscopic bin, and present minimal impacts from systematic effects. We detect
significant absorption from CO$_2$ (28.5ensuremathσ) and H$_2$O (21.5ensuremathσ),
and identify SO$_2$ as the source of absorption at 4.1 ensuremathμm (4.8ensuremathσ).
Best-fit atmospheric models range between 3 and 10 times solar metallicity, with
sub-solar to solar C/O ratios. These results, including the detection of SO$_2$,
underscore the importance of characterizing the chemistry in exoplanet atmospheres
and showcase NIRSpec G395H as an excellent mode for time-series observations over
this critical wavelength range$^10$.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Early Release Science of the exoplanet WASP-39b with JWST NIRSpec PRISM</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publications/2023-natur-614-659-r.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publications/2023-natur-614-659-r.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Transmission spectroscopy$^1-3$ of exoplanets has revealed signatures of
water vapour, aerosols and alkali metals in a few dozen exoplanet atmospheres$^4,5$.
However, these previous inferences with the Hubble and Spitzer Space Telescopes
were hindered by the observations&amp;rsquo; relatively narrow wavelength range and spectral
resolving power, which precluded the unambiguous identification of other chemical
species—in particular the primary carbon-bearing molecules$^6,7$. Here we report
a broad-wavelength 0.5-5.5 textmum atmospheric transmission spectrum of WASP-39b$^8$,
a 1,200 K, roughly Saturn-mass, Jupiter-radius exoplanet, measured with the JWST
NIRSpec&amp;rsquo;s PRISM mode$^9$ as part of the JWST Transiting Exoplanet Community Early
Release Science Team Program$^10-12$. We robustly detect several chemical species
at high significance, including Na (19σ), H$_2$O (33σ), CO$_2$
(28σ) and CO (7σ). The non-detection of CH$_4$, combined with
a strong CO$_2$ feature, favours atmospheric models with a super-solar atmospheric
metallicity. An unanticipated absorption feature at 4 textmum is best explained
by SO$_2$ (2.7σ), which could be a tracer of atmospheric photochemistry.
These observations demonstrate JWST&amp;rsquo;s sensitivity to a rich diversity of exoplanet
compositions and chemical processes.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>On the Volatile Enrichments and Heavy Element Content in HD189733b</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publications/2011-ap-j-727-77-m.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Feb 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publications/2011-ap-j-727-77-m.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Add the &lt;strong&gt;full text&lt;/strong&gt; or &lt;strong&gt;supplementary notes&lt;/strong&gt; for the publication here using Markdown formatting.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
