<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Planets and Satellites: Individual: Wasp-18 B | Nicolas Iro</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/tag/planets-and-satellites-individual-wasp-18-b.html</link>
      <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/tag/planets-and-satellites-individual-wasp-18-b/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Planets and Satellites: Individual: Wasp-18 B</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 01 Jul 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>http://localhost:1313/media/logo_hu_a8d074ae3d848875.png</url>
      <title>Planets and Satellites: Individual: Wasp-18 B</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/tag/planets-and-satellites-individual-wasp-18-b.html</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dark skies of the slightly eccentric WASP-18 b from its optical-to-infrared dayside emission</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publications/2025-aa-699-a-150-d.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jul 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publications/2025-aa-699-a-150-d.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Context. Ultra-hot Jupiters (UHJs) are gas giant exoplanets that are strongly
irradiated by their star, setting intense molecular dissociation that leads to atmospheric
chemistry dominated by ions and atoms. These conditions inhibit day-to-night heat
redistribution, which results in high temperature contrasts. Phase-curve observations
over several passbands offer insights on the thermal structure and properties of
these extreme atmospheres. Aims. We aim to perform a joint analysis of multiple
observations of WASP-18 b from the visible to the mid- infrared, using data from
CHEOPS, TESS, and Spitzer. Our purpose is to characterise the planetary atmosphere
with a consistent view over the large wavelength range covered, including JWST data.
Methods. We implemented a model for the planetary signal including transits, occultations,
phase signal, ellipsoidal variations, Doppler boosting, and light travel time. We
performed a joint fit of more than 250 eclipse events and derived the atmospheric
properties using general circulation models (GCMs) and retrieval analyses. Results.
We obtained new ephemerides with unprecedented precisions of 1 second and 1.4 millisecond
on the time of inferior conjunction and orbital period, respectively. We computed
a planetary radius of R $_ p $ = 1.1926 ensuremath± 0.0077 R $_ J $ with a precision
of 0.65% (or 550 km). Based on a timing inconsistency with JWST, we discuss and
confirm the orbital eccentricity (e = 0.00852 ensuremath± 0.00091). We also constrain
the argument of periastron to ensuremathømega = 261.9$_‑1.4$ $^+1.3$ deg. We show
that the large dayside emission implies the presence of magnetic drag and super-solar
metallicity. We find a steep thermally inverted gradient in the planetary atmosphere,
which is common for UHJs. We detected the presence of strong CO emission lines at
4.5 ensuremathμm from an excess of dayside brightness in the Spitzer/IRAC/Channel
2 passband. Using these models to constrain the reflected contribution in the CHEOPS
passband, we derived an extremely low geometric albedo of A$_g$ $^CHEOPS$ = 0.027
ensuremath± 0.011. Conclusions. The orbital eccentricity remains a potential challenge
for planetary dynamics that might require further study given the short-period massive
planet and despite the young age of the system. The characterisation of the atmosphere
of WASP-18 b reveals the necessity to account for magnetic friction and super-solar
metallicity to explain the full picture of the dayside emission. We find the planetary
dayside to be extremely unreflective; however, when juxtaposing TESS and CHEOPS
data, we get hints of increased scattering efficiency in the visible, likely due
to Rayleigh scattering.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
