<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Planets and Satellites: Composition | Nicolas Iro</title><link>https://ironick.github.io/tag/planets-and-satellites-composition.html</link><atom:link href="https://ironick.github.io/tag/planets-and-satellites-composition/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><description>Planets and Satellites: Composition</description><generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 01 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><image><url>https://ironick.github.io/media/logo_hu3811882414585691295.png</url><title>Planets and Satellites: Composition</title><link>https://ironick.github.io/tag/planets-and-satellites-composition.html</link></image><item><title>Understanding the atmospheric properties and chemical composition of the ultra-hot Jupiter HAT-P-7b. II. Mapping the effects of gas kinetics</title><link>https://ironick.github.io/publications/2020-aa-635-a-31-m.html</link><pubDate>Sun, 01 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ironick.github.io/publications/2020-aa-635-a-31-m.html</guid><description>&lt;p>Aims: The atmospheres of ultra-hot Jupiters (UHJs) are commonly considered
to be at thermochemical equilibrium. We aim to provide disequilibrium chemistry
maps for a global understanding of the chemistry in the atmosphere of HAT-P-7b and
assess the importance of disequilibrium chemistry on UHJs. Methods: We applied
a hierarchical modeling approach using 97 1D atmospheric profiles from a 3D general
circulation model of HAT-P-7b. For each atmospheric 1D profile, we evaluated our
kinetic cloud formation model consistently with the local gas-phase composition
in chemical equilibrium. This served as input to study the quenching of dominating
CHNO- binding molecules. We evaluated quenching results from a zeroth- order approximation
in comparison to a kinetic gas-phase approach. Results: We find that the zeroth-order
approach of estimating quenching points agrees well with the full gas-kinetic modeling
results. However, it underestimates the quenching levels by about one order of magnitude
at high temperatures. Chemical disequilibrium has the greatest effect on the nightside
and morning abundance of species such as H, H$_2$O, CH$_4$, CO$_2$, HCN, and all
C$_n$H$_m$ molecules; heavier C$_n$H$_m$ molecules are more affected by disequilibrium
processes. The CO abundance, however, is affected only marginally. While dayside
abundances also notably change, those around the evening terminator of HAT-P-7b
are the least affected by disequilibrium processes. The latter finding may partially
explain the consistency of observed transmission spectra of UHJs with atmospheres
in thermochemical equilibrium. Photochemistry only negligibly affects molecular
abundances and quenching levels. Conclusions: In general, the quenching points
of the atmosphere of HAT-P-7b are at much lower pressures than in the cooler hot-jupiters.
We propose several avenues to determining the effect of disequilibrium processes
on UHJs that are in general based on abundance and opacity measurements at different
local times. It remains a challenge to completely disentangle this from the chemical
effects of clouds and that of a primordial nonsolar abundance.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>The atmospheric chemistry of the warm Neptune GJ 3470b: Influence of metallicity and temperature on the CH$_4$/CO ratio</title><link>https://ironick.github.io/publications/2014-aa-562-a-51-v.html</link><pubDate>Sat, 01 Feb 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ironick.github.io/publications/2014-aa-562-a-51-v.html</guid><description>&lt;p>Add the &lt;strong>full text&lt;/strong> or &lt;strong>supplementary notes&lt;/strong> for the publication here using Markdown formatting.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>The Puzzling Chemical Composition of GJ 436b's Atmosphere: Influence of Tidal Heating on the Chemistry</title><link>https://ironick.github.io/publications/2014-ap-j-781-68-a.html</link><pubDate>Sat, 01 Feb 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ironick.github.io/publications/2014-ap-j-781-68-a.html</guid><description>&lt;p>Add the &lt;strong>full text&lt;/strong> or &lt;strong>supplementary notes&lt;/strong> for the publication here using Markdown formatting.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>On the Volatile Enrichments and Heavy Element Content in HD189733b</title><link>https://ironick.github.io/publications/2011-ap-j-727-77-m.html</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Feb 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ironick.github.io/publications/2011-ap-j-727-77-m.html</guid><description>&lt;p>Add the &lt;strong>full text&lt;/strong> or &lt;strong>supplementary notes&lt;/strong> for the publication here using Markdown formatting.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>