<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Transmission Spectroscopy | Nicolas Iro</title><link>https://ironick.github.io/tag/transmission-spectroscopy.html</link><atom:link href="https://ironick.github.io/tag/transmission-spectroscopy/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><description>Transmission Spectroscopy</description><generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 01 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><image><url>https://ironick.github.io/media/logo_hu3811882414585691295.png</url><title>Transmission Spectroscopy</title><link>https://ironick.github.io/tag/transmission-spectroscopy.html</link></image><item><title>Detection of Carbon Monoxide's 4.6 Micron Fundamental Band Structure in WASP-39b's Atmosphere with JWST NIRSpec G395H</title><link>https://ironick.github.io/publications/2023-ap-j-949-l-15-g.html</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ironick.github.io/publications/2023-ap-j-949-l-15-g.html</guid><description>&lt;p>Carbon monoxide (CO) is predicted to be the dominant carbon-bearing molecule
in giant planet atmospheres and, along with water, is important for discerning the
oxygen and therefore carbon-to- oxygen ratio of these planets. The fundamental absorption
mode of CO has a broad, double-branched structure composed of many individual absorption
lines from 4.3 to 5.1 ensuremathμm, which can now be spectroscopically measured
with JWST. Here we present a technique for detecting the rotational sub-band structure
of CO at medium resolution with the NIRSpec G395H instrument. We use a single transit
observation of the hot Jupiter WASP-39b from the JWST Transiting Exoplanet Community
Early Release Science (JTEC ERS) program at the native resolution of the instrument
(R åisebox-0.5ex~ 2700) to resolve the CO absorption structure. We robustly detect
absorption by CO, with an increase in transit depth of 264 ensuremath± 68 ppm, in
agreement with the predicted CO contribution from the best-fit model at low resolution.
This detection confirms our theoretical expectations that CO is the dominant carbon-bearing
molecule in WASP-39b&amp;rsquo;s atmosphere and further supports the conclusions of low C/O
and supersolar metallicities presented in the JTEC ERS papers for WASP-39b.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>