<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Molecular Signatures | Nicolas Iro</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/tag/molecular-signatures.html</link>
      <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/tag/molecular-signatures/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Molecular Signatures</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 01 Nov 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>http://localhost:1313/media/logo_hu_a8d074ae3d848875.png</url>
      <title>Molecular Signatures</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/tag/molecular-signatures.html</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>A chemical survey of exoplanets with ARIEL</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publications/2018-ex-a-46-135-t.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Nov 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publications/2018-ex-a-46-135-t.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Thousands of exoplanets have now been discovered with a huge range of masses,
sizes and orbits: from rocky Earth-like planets to large gas giants grazing the
surface of their host star. However, the essential nature of these exoplanets
remains largely mysterious: there is no known, discernible pattern linking the
presence, size, or orbital parameters of a planet to the nature of its parent
star. We have little idea whether the chemistry of a planet is linked to its formation
environment, or whether the type of host star drives the physics and chemistry
of the planet&amp;rsquo;s birth, and evolution. ARIEL was conceived to observe a large number
( 1000) of transiting planets for statistical understanding, including gas giants,
Neptunes, super-Earths and Earth-size planets around a range of host star types
using transit spectroscopy in the 1.25-7.8 ensuremathμm spectral range and multiple
narrow-band photometry in the optical. ARIEL will focus on warm and hot planets
to take advantage of their well-mixed atmospheres which should show minimal condensation
and sequestration of high-Z materials compared to their colder Solar System siblings.
Said warm and hot atmospheres are expected to be more representative of the planetary
bulk composition. Observations of these warm/hot exoplanets, and in particular
of their elemental composition (especially C, O, N, S, Si), will allow the understanding
of the early stages of planetary and atmospheric formation during the nebular
phase and the following few million years. ARIEL will thus provide a representative
picture of the chemical nature of the exoplanets and relate this directly to the
type and chemical environment of the host star. ARIEL is designed as a dedicated
survey mission for combined-light spectroscopy, capable of observing a large and
well-defined planet sample within its 4-year mission lifetime. Transit, eclipse
and phase-curve spectroscopy methods, whereby the signal from the star and planet
are differentiated using knowledge of the planetary ephemerides, allow us to measure
atmospheric signals from the planet at levels of 10-100 part per million (ppm)
relative to the star and, given the bright nature of targets, also allows more
sophisticated techniques, such as eclipse mapping, to give a deeper insight into
the nature of the atmosphere. These types of observations require a stable payload
and satellite platform with broad, instantaneous wavelength coverage to detect
many molecular species, probe the thermal structure, identify clouds and monitor
the stellar activity. The wavelength range proposed covers all the expected major
atmospheric gases from e.g. H$_2$O, CO$_2$, CH$_4$ NH$_3$, HCN, H$_2$S through
to the more exotic metallic compounds, such as TiO, VO, and condensed species.
Simulations of ARIEL performance in conducting exoplanet surveys have been performed&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;using conservative estimates of mission performance and a full model of all
significant noise sources in the measurement&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;using a list of potential ARIEL targets that incorporates the latest available exoplanet statistics.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The conclusion
at the end of the Phase A study, is that ARIEL - in line with the stated mission
objectives - will be able to observe about 1000 exoplanets depending on the details
of the adopted survey strategy, thus confirming the feasibility of the main science
objectives.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
